<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dagon's fall before the Ark, or, The smoak of the bottomless pit scoured away by the breath of the Lords mouth, and by the brightness of his coming written primarily, as a testimony for the Lord, his wisdom ... : secondarily, as testimony against the old serpent his wisdom, which is foolishness with God ... : wherein as in a glass, teachers in schools and colledges may see their concern, neither Christian nor warrantable / by Thomas Lawson.</title>
            <author>Lawson, Thomas, 1630-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L724</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226480</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355030</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355030</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110312</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110312)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1743:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dagon's fall before the Ark, or, The smoak of the bottomless pit scoured away by the breath of the Lords mouth, and by the brightness of his coming written primarily, as a testimony for the Lord, his wisdom ... : secondarily, as testimony against the old serpent his wisdom, which is foolishness with God ... : wherein as in a glass, teachers in schools and colledges may see their concern, neither Christian nor warrantable / by Thomas Lawson.</title>
                  <author>Lawson, Thomas, 1630-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 94 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Education --  Philosophy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian education --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110312:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dagon's Fall</hi> Before the ARK.</p>
            <p>OR, The Smoak of the Bottomleſs Pit ſcoured away, by the breath of the Lords mouth, and by the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his coming.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN. Primarily, As a Teſtimony for the Lord, his Wiſdom, Creation, products of his Power; uſeful and neceſſary Knowledge, capacitating people for the concerns of this Life.</p>
            <p>Secondarily, As a Teſtimony againſt the Old Serpent his wiſdom, which is fooliſhneſs with God, his Arts, Inventions, Comedies or Interludes, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies, laſcivious Poems, frivolous Fables, ſpoiling Philoſophy, taught in Chriſtian Schools.</p>
            <p>Wherein, as in a Glaſs, Teachers in Schools and Colledges may ſee their concern, neither Chriſtian, nor warrantable.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Lawſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Qui novit utilia, non qui multa, ſapiens habendas.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Orat. D. Rainoldi.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Id verum, quod prius, prius, quod ab initio, ab initio, quod ab Apoſtolis.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tertul.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> nunquam è beatitudinis paradiſo pulſus fuiſſet, niſi, Serpente Magiſtro, didiciſſet ſcire bonum &amp; malum.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cornel. Agrip. de Van. Scient.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the year 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:110312:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110312:2"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS Of the following TREATISE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 1.</label> OF Heavenly wiſdom, and her Children, being true and divine Philoſophers.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 2.</label> Of the riſe and progreſs of Serpentine wiſdom, that is, the wiſdom of this World.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 3.</label> Of the riſe and progreſs of Pagan Philoſophy, worldly wiſdom, crept in among the Profeſſors of Christianity, and Testimonies of the Holy men of God against the ſame.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 4.</label> A rehearſal of Testimonies, borne by ſeveral men eminent in the Church, ſince the Apostles days, against Heathen learning, or the teaching of it, in Chriſtian Schools, as of others.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:110312:3"/>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 5.</label> A <hi>Memento</hi> to Schoolmaſters and Tutors, to turn from Heathen, to the Godly and Chriſtian education of Youth; as alſo of the riſe of Christian Schools, and how the ſame came to be corrupted.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 6.</label> Lastly, a few <hi>Queries</hi> ſoberly propoſed to the conſideration of ſuch as teach Heathen Authors in Christian Schools.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110312:3"/>
            <head>DAGON'S Fall before the ARK.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of Heavenly Wiſdom, and her Children, being true and divine Philoſophers.</head>
               <p>THere is a wiſdom, whoſe Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize tranſcends the Merchandize of Silver, whoſe gain ſurmounts the gain of the pureſt Gold, more precious than Rubies, than the Onyx, Saphire, Chryſtal, Coral, or Topaz of <hi>Ethiopia;</hi> her ways are ways of pleaſantneſs, all her paths are peace; ſhe is a Tree of Life; By her Kings reign, and Princes decree juſtice; her fruit is better than Gold, her revenue than choice Silver; ſhe was from everlaſting, or ever the Earth was, before the Depths, before the Fountains abounding with waters, before the Mountains were ſettled, before the Hills towered up, before the Curtain of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens was prepared, before the Clouds above were eſtabliſhed, before the Sea had its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, before the foundation of the Earth was appointed, before the Rain, or pearly drops
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110312:4"/>of Dew, before the Ice, and hoary froſt of Heaven, before the <hi>Pleides,</hi> and the bands of <hi>Orion,</hi> before <hi>Mazzaroth, Arcturus,</hi> and his Sons, before the Bottles of Heaven were poured out: In this wiſdom <hi>Adam</hi> was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in purity, innocency, and righteouſneſs, a noble extract; in this, he had dominion over the Fiſh of the Sea, over the Fowl of the Air, over the Cattle, over all the Earth, and over every creeping thing; through the virtue and influence of this, he knew his Creator, and had an underſtanding of the natures and properties of the Creation, and gave names to all Cattle, and to the Fowl of the Air, and to every Beaſt of the Field, and that ſignificant names.</p>
               <p>Through this, <hi>Adam</hi> was all fair, through a Garment conferred upon him, out of the Wardrobe of Eternity, while in the love and power of this, he was a true Divine Philoſopher; that is, a Lover of wiſdom, not tainted by the intermixture of the Serpent, not his enſnaring inventions. The living God (ſaith the Paraphraſt on the <hi>Samaritan Pentateuch</hi>) formed <hi>Adam,</hi> and filled him with the Spirit of wiſdom and knowledge, that from him, as from a Fountain, all uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Arts and Sciences might flow unto his poſterity; for beſides the ſecret virtues of living Creatures, of Plants, of Stones, of Metals, and Minerals, he perfectly knew
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110312:4"/>the influences of ſupernal Bodies, ſaith <hi>Theoph. Gale.</hi> And if <hi>Adam</hi> and his poſterity had perſevered in that ſtate of Heavenly wiſdom, innocency and ſincerity, in which he was created, here had been no defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Aſtrologers, Charmers, Conſulters with Familiar Spirits, Diviners, Inchanters, Magicians, Nicromancers, Obſervers of Times, Prognoſticators, Soothſayers, Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Witches, Wizards, who all derive their power, and fooliſh infernal knowledge, from thoſe lying Lips, which ſeduced <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> from the Royal Court of the Lords bleſſed preſence, into the dead Sea of deluſions, and wicked eſtrangments from God.</p>
               <p>Yea I ſay, if <hi>Adam</hi> and his poſterity had kept their ſtanding in Heavenly wiſdoms dominion, we had had no laſcivious Poems, no wanton Comedies, no vain Tragedies, no fooliſh Fables, no bewitching Orations, no ſpoiling Philoſophy, no Pagan Ethicks, Phyſicks, or Metaphyſicks, which are the infatuating dregs of the Helliſh dead Sea, the ſmoak of the bottomleſs Pit, as hereafter may more fully be touched.</p>
               <p>About the tenth Generation after the Floud, <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the faithful, grew up among the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> in the ſaving knowledge of the Lord; he loved Heavenly wiſdom, and the products thereof, the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110312:5"/>ſo was a true Philoſopher; through Faith he obtained a good report, and among other things this record remains concerning him, <hi>Shall I hide from Abraham,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>the thing which I do,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For I know him, that he will command his children, and his houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, to do juſtice and judgment,</hi> Gen. 18.17, 18, 19. This was the ſum of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Doctrine to his Family; this he, and the faithful Patriarchs taught, juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heavenly wiſdom, and the bleſſed order of it: Heatheniſm they kept out, through the ſhield of Faith; and who are of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> they do the works of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſhun Heatheniſm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> grew up in the knowledge of the living God, and of the Creation; he loved the wiſdom that was from above, ſo was a true Divine Philoſopher. <hi>Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus</hi> wrote of him, that he was a Divine and a Prophet.</p>
               <p>Now if any alledge, That <hi>Moſes was learned in all the wiſdom of the Egyptians,</hi> (that is, in prophane Arts and Sciences) <hi>and was mighty in words and in deeds,</hi> Acts 7.22.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, True it is, <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſo learned, which <hi>Egyptian</hi> learning (faith <hi>Pererius</hi>) was Pagan Mathematicks, Ethicks, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicks, Metaphyſicks, a chief part whereof
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110312:5"/>was Hieroglyphicks; but when he was to be concern'd for the living God, to go his Meſſage, ſee how his prophane Arts and Sciences, the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Hieroglyphicks, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered him, he was mute, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.10, 11, 12. he ſaid to the Lord, <hi>O my Lord, I am not elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent:</hi> The Lord ſaid unto him, <hi>Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore go, and I will be with thy mouth, and teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay.</hi> Here he is drawn from the dirty puddle of prophane Arts and Sciences, <hi>Egyptian</hi> wiſdom, Pagan Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks, Hieroglyphicks: In a word from thoſe lying lips, which deceived <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and all the inventions thereof, even to the mouth of God, the Well-ſpring of pure wiſdom, ſavoury knowledge, and ſound underſtanding. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> being brought to that mouth, which taught <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in the ſtate of innocency, he ſtreamed out Heavenly eloquence, ſaying, <hi>My doctrine ſhall drop as the rain, my ſpeech ſhall diſtill as the dew, as the ſmall rain upon the tender herb, and as the ſhowers upon the graſs,</hi> Deut. 32.2. No prophane Arts nor Sciences, no <hi>Egyptian</hi> Mathematicks, no Hieroglyphicks, no Pagan Ethicks, Phyſicks or Metaphyſicks dropped out of his mouth.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Moſes</hi> was excellent in the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> yet he hath left us nothing thereof in writing, nor encouraged any to learn the ſame: <hi>Ambroſe</hi> gives the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110312:6"/>reaſon of this, becauſe he had received Gods Spirit, and Heavenly wiſdom thereby; ſo as Gods Servant was faithful in all his houſe, he preſerr'd Heavenly Truth before vain Earthly Philoſophy, and concern'd himſelf only in things whoſe tendency were to the furtherance of Faith. <hi>Trapp</hi> on the <hi>Acts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Exo 23.13. <hi>In all things that I have ſaid unto you, be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect, and make no mention of the names of other gods, neither let it be heard out of thy mouth.</hi> He preached not up <hi>Egyptian</hi> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor the <hi>Egyptian</hi> gods, nor any gods of the Heathen, but to raze the memorial of them from off the face of the Earth, ſaying, <hi>make no mention of the names of other gods:</hi> but Schools and Colledges ſhew forth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spirit, ringing with the names of <hi>Mars, Bacchus, Apollo,</hi> and multitudes more, which I forbear to mention.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaking of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, Judgments, and Commandments of the Lord, received from Heaven, for the edification of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall teach them to your children; when thou ſitteſt in thine houſe, when thou walkest by the way, when thou lieſt down, when thou riſeſt up,</hi> Deut. 11.19. Here was Heavenly wiſdom, Statutes, Judgments and Commandments, received from the mouth of Eternity, to be taught to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110312:6"/>not <hi>Egyptian</hi> Mathematicks, Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphicks, Ethicks, Phyſicks, Metaphyſicks, not laſcivious Poems, Comedies. Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Fables, ſpoiling Philoſophy, wherewith Schools and Colledges, though profeſſing Chriſtianity and Reformation, now abound. Further <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to <hi>Iſrael, When thou art come into the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, thou ſhalt not learn to do after the abominations of thoſe Nations,</hi> Deut. 18.9. Now it is ſealed in my inward parts, that Heathen Poems, Pagan Philoſophy, fooliſh Comedies, Tragedies, Fables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> taught in the Schools of Chriſtendom, are abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſight of the Lord, though of high eſteem among men, and driven as it were <hi>vi &amp; armis,</hi> by force of Arms into tender years.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſhua</hi> grew up in the pure knowledge of the Lord, received Heavenly wiſdom, walked in it, prized it above the Gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> ſo was a true Philoſopher, God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be with him, as he was with <hi>Moſes, Joſ.</hi> 1.5. he taught <hi>Iſrael</hi> not to be defiled with the abomination of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, nor to make mention of the names of their gods, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 23. ſo the Serpent and his inventions he fenced out: Schools and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges now profeſſing Chriſtianity, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and the Goſpel, teaching the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inventions of the Heathen, are not come
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110312:7"/>to <hi>Moſes,</hi> who forbad theſe things, death reigns there.</p>
               <p>I am eaſie to perſwade (ſaith <hi>Theophilus Gale</hi>) that the old <hi>Egyptians</hi> learned many things of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> concerning the Soul, and the originality, immateriality, immortality, and ſtate of it after death; and not only from him, but from the Patriarchs, and from the writings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they received many things, which they ſtained with the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their own inventions, as 'tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded. As for ſaving knowledge, pure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, ſound judgment, theſe are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the Lord, the Well-ſpring of life. After that <hi>Joſeph</hi> had given <hi>Pharoah</hi> advice, concerning the enſuing Famine, and other things, <hi>Pharoah</hi> prized him above all the Wiſe-men of <hi>Egypt,</hi> Sorcerers, Magicians, Inchanters, ſaying, <hi>Can we find ſuch a one as this is, a man in whom the Spirit of God is?</hi> Further he ſaid unto <hi>Joſeph, In as much as God hath ſhewed thee all this, there is none ſo diſcreet and wiſe as thou art,</hi> Gen. 41.38, 39. Thus the wiſdom and diſcretion received from the mouth of God, was preferr'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſdom received otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bezaleel</hi> was filled with the Spirit of God in wiſdom, in underſtanding, and in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and in all manner of workmanſhip, to work in Gold, and in Silver, and in Braſs, in cutting of Stones, in carving of Timber,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110312:7"/>for the building of the Tabernacle, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. Thus he was qualified from Heaven, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ethnick education, ſo was a true Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher; implying, that ſuch as under the Evangelical diſpenſation, are appointed for the building up of the living Tabernacle, Sons or Daughters, their qualification for that work is from Heaven, and not from below.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Lord gave unto him a wiſe and underſtanding heart, whereby he knew the Lord, and had great underſtanding in the Lords Creation, without Ethnick edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, he was a true Philoſopher, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.12. he builded the Temple, and overlaid it within with pure Gold, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. What implies this? but that ſuch as under the Goſpel miniſtration, are prepared for the building up of the Spiritual Temple, be they Sons or Daughters, their preparation is of the Lord; and that he had a clear under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Lords Creation, is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable from Scripture records, for he ſpake of Trees, from the Cedar tree that is in <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon,</hi> even unto the Hyſop that ſpringeth out of the Wall; he ſpake alſo of Beaſts, and of Fowl, and of creeping things, and of Fiſhes, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1. his wiſdom excelled all the wiſdom of the Eaſt-Country, and all the wiſdom of <hi>Egypt;</hi> ſo that the Queen of the South, whom the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Chronicles call
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110312:8"/>
                  <hi>Mackeda,</hi> came from the uttermoſt parts of the Earth to hear the wiſdom of <hi>Solomon;</hi> who was ſo taken with the Heavenly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that dropped out of his mouth, that ſhe could have been content to have changed her Throne for his Foot ſtool; he ſed her not with Ethnick Serpentine wiſdom, but with what was Spiritual and Divine. <hi>Trapp</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> taught no Pagan Philoſophy, no Heatheniſm, but the perfect Law, and pure Statutes of the Lord, the Lord was with him, <hi>2 Chron.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> cauſed no Pagan Philoſophy, no Heatheniſm, no ſaln wiſdom to be taught in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to old or young; but going from <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the good hand of God being upon him, he ſought the Law of the Lord, and taught the Statutes and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord in <hi>Iſrael, Ezra</hi> 7. Now who neglect the wiſdom from above, and propagate Earthly Serpentine wiſdom, which is from below, ſuch are in <hi>Babylon,</hi> not come to the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job</hi> of the Land of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z,</hi> perfect and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, fearing God and eſchewing evil, he knew that his Redeemer lived in the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Redeemer; he knew the Lord, and ſaw much into the Creation of the Lord, ſo was a true and Divine Philoſopher. That he was wiſe in the Creation, it appears, he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110312:8"/>ſpake of Thunder, of Vapours, of Clouds, of Rain, of Snow, of Hail, of the Sea, of Fountain, of Metals, as Gold, Silver, Iron, Braſs, of Stones, of precious Stones, of ſubterraneous Fire, of Stars, of living Creatures, of Earthquakes, of <hi>Arcturus, Orion,</hi> and the <hi>Pleides,</hi> of the Sun, of the Heavens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſuph</hi> in the wiſdom of God, deſired that the pure Statutes and Judgments of the Lord, might be taught to Children, not the ways of the Heathen, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.5, 6, 7. he made Covenant with <hi>Jacob,</hi> and gave <hi>Iſrael</hi> a Law, which he commanded our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers to teach their Children, that their poſterity might know it, and the Children which were yet unborn.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſeaſoned with the inſpiration of the Almighty, prized the wiſdom from above; ſpeaking of the Plow-man, he ſaid, <hi>God doth instruct him to diſcretion, and doth teach him,</hi> Iſa. 28. So the Plow-man that is center'd in the fear of the Lord, is taught of the Lord diſcretion in his calling, without Heathen education. Yea, and propheſying of the glory of the Evangelical diſpenſation, he teſtified thus, <hi>They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy mountain, for the earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the ſea,</hi> Iſa. 11.9. Mark, here the knowledge of the Lord is preach'd up, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110312:9"/>knowledge which he teaches, which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of: this ſhuts out the knowledge and wiſdom of this world, brought in by the old Serpent, the god of this world.</p>
               <p>The living God gave knowledge and skill in all learning and wiſdom, unto <hi>Daniel, Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego;</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> had underſtanding in all Viſions and Dreams; and this was by the teaching of the Lord, without recourſe to Ethnick ſtudy and education, <hi>Dan.</hi> 1. the King found them ten times wiſer then all his Magicians and Aſtrologers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the chaff to the wheat, ſaith the Lord?</hi> Jer. 23.28. all products of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, all laſcivious Poems, wanton Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, vain Tragedies, frivolous Fables, ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Philoſophy, the wiſdom of the world, which is fooliſhneſs with God; theſe are but as Chaff, to be ſcattered by Chriſts Fan.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> under the Moſaical diſpenſation, had Schools in every City and Province, built upon Hills, as Writers tell us; there is mention of the Hill <hi>Moreb,</hi> that is, the Hill of the Teacher, <hi>Judg.</hi> 7.1. In theſe, while they kept the charge of the Lord, there was nothing taught but the knowledge of the Lord, and of his Creation: In theſe (ſaith <hi>Theophilus Gale</hi>) they taught the Prieſts and Levites their Offices, being cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of God thereunto.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:110312:9"/>
               <p>In every Age and Generation, ſuch as were truly made alive unto God, they held out the wiſdom of God, as the only Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhing treaſure, and bare teſtimony againſt the wiſdom of the fleſh, pernicious as the poyſon of Alps.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fear of the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>is the beginning of wiſdom, and the knowledge of the holy is underſtanding,</hi> Pro. 9.10. and who come not to the beginning of wiſdom, the fear of the Lord, ſuch are ſtrangers to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdom, and to the precious effects thereof; now as for laſcivious Poems, fooliſh Comedies, vain Tragedies, frivolous Fables, bewitching Orations, ſpoyling Philoſophy, taught in Chriſtian Schools; theſe proceeded from men not center'd in the fear of the Lord, the ſame is fooliſhneſs with God. The Law of thy mouth (ſaid the man of God) is dearer unto me then thouſands of Gold and Silver; Here wiſdom, knowledge and underſtanding, and ſound Judgement is prefer'd before earthly treaſures; mark this, it was the Law of the mouth of the Lord, that he thus prized, not earthly, ſenſual, and deviliſh wiſdom, the muddy and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous ſtreams of the Serpent.</p>
               <p>We read of certain Libertines, <hi>Cyrenians, Alexandrians, Cilicians</hi> and <hi>Aſians,</hi> puft up with the breath of the Serpents bellows, theſe in the wiſdom of the fleſh diſputed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110312:10"/>with <hi>Stephen,</hi> who was in the wiſdom of the ſpirit <hi>and they were not able to reſiſt the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and the ſpirit by which he ſpake,</hi> Acts. 6.9, 10. <hi>Paul</hi> held out nothing but Chriſt, and the ſame Serpentine-wiſdom in Inſtruments of all ſorts, oppoſes and gainſays the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breakings of Heavenly wiſdom, in this our Age, and many witneſſes raiſed out of the duſt, notwithſtanding on their feet in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of Truth; know that the Lord is now at work, and that the Myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity muſt be caſt out, not by outward Sword, Battle, Ax, or any Inſtruments of War, but by the breath of the Lords mouth, and by the brightneſs of his coming.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> though he was profound in natural Parts, Abilities, and acquired accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet when Chriſt was revealed in him, the Teacher of Heavenly wiſdom, at <hi>Rome,</hi> as at other places, he Preached the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and the things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the Lord Jeſus, and plentious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption in him, not one word of Pagan Philoſophy, <hi>Acts.</hi> 28.30, 31.</p>
               <p>Further <hi>Paul</hi> who had the mind of Chriſt, he, at <hi>Corinth</hi> a City abounding with Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers and Oratours, Preached up the wiſdom of God, and bare record againſt the wiſdom of the fleſh; Heathen Philoſophy, ſaying, we ſpeak wiſdom among them that are perfect, yet not the wiſdom of this world,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110312:10"/>nor of the Princes of this world, which comes to nought: Further faith he, <hi>Which things alſo we ſpeak, not in the words which mans wiſdom teacheth, but which the Holy Ghost teacheth,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. <hi>and</hi> 1 Cor. 2.6.13.</p>
               <p>Further, <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt, ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>in him are hid all the treaſures of wiſdom and knowledge,</hi> Coloſ. 2.3. out of Chriſt, then there is no true wiſdom or ſolid comfort to be found, the depth ſaith, <hi>it is not in me, the worlds Wizards cannot help any to it,</hi> Jer. 8.9. Lo, they have rejected the word of the Lord, and what wiſdom is in them? true it is, who rejected the in-dwelling word of Faith, or Patience, of Reconcilation, of Heavenly Wiſdom, there is no wiſdom in them, but unprofitable droſs of fooliſhneſs.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing all the treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge are in Chriſt, no part of this treaſure is left out, to inrich Heathen Philoſophy, which the Goſpel caſts out as a ſandy, dry, barren, deſolate and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thing, ſeeing theſe treaſures, all theſe treaſures are in Chriſt, the ſame then are to be ſought of, and in Chriſt, not as <hi>Ariſtotle, Plato,</hi> or any other of the worlds Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, being but broken Ciſterns, not hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the water of life, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpoke feeling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <hi>the Lord gives wiſdom, out of his mouth comes knowledge and understanding,</hi> Pro. 2.6</p>
               <p>While <hi>Adam</hi> ſtood to the Lords teaching.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110312:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:110312:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:110312:12"/>he received the treaſures of Heavenly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſound knowledge and underſtanding, peace, joy, and conſolation as a ſtream; but turning aſide to the Serpents teaching, to his mouth, he left his Dominion in the Lord, his bleſſed State; and out of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents mouth proceeded all wickedneſs, all fleſhly wiſdom, all frivolous Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences now taught in Chriſtian Schools (ſo called:) ſo, who run to Pagan Philoſophers, as <hi>Ariſtotle, Plato,</hi> or any laſcivious Poet, Comedian, Tragedian, they revolt from Chriſt the treaſury of Heavenly wiſdom: <hi>Who gives eternal life, and an everlaſting In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and run a Whoring after faln wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſo are guilty of</hi> Iſraels <hi>ſin,</hi> Jer. 2.13. <hi>Paul</hi> was firſt brought up at the feet of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliel,</hi> born in <hi>Tarſus,</hi> that had read <hi>Aratus, Meander</hi> and <hi>Epimanides,</hi> Authors, is clear by what he cited; but while he ſtood in the Ethnick mind, he was a grand perſecutor, idolized his Ethnick education; but Chriſt being revealed in him, the Store-houſe of Heavenly wiſdom, knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; then he accounted Ethnick Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as dung and droſs, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7, 8 . All his idolized, magnified, and highly prized Arts, Parts and Attainments, of faln wiſdom, he accounted but as dung, wiſdom from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove being revealed; the Lord called <hi>Paul</hi> wiſe in naturals, and many that were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110312:12"/>thereof to Preach the everlaſting Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Further, <hi>Paul</hi> in the wiſdom from above at the Univerſity of <hi>Athens,</hi> he reproved their Idolatry, Superſtition and Heatheniſm; <hi>he taught nothing but the living God, and Christ Jeſus,</hi> Acts 17. In the comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, he ſaw theſe Philoſophers, Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans, Stoicks, and withſtood them; but they in the gloomy region of Heatheniſm ſaw not him, nor the Heavenly wiſdom that he Preached, ſo called him a babler; yet he fought not in vain but conquered ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral, ſo prevailed, that many renounced their Pagan Philoſophy, and curious Artiſts burned their Books of earthly Satanical wiſdom; thus <hi>Paul</hi> in the Armour of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs diſarmed theſe pagan Philoſophers, the Devils Champions, <hi>and brought them to be</hi> Sions <hi>Converts to receive her Armour</hi> Acts 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James</hi> one of the Lords worthies, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the twelve Tribes ſcattered, ſaid, <hi>if any of you lack wiſdom, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberally,</hi> James 1.5. He commends the ignorant to the Lord, not to <hi>Ariſtotle, Plato,</hi> nor to any other Pagan Philoſopher.</p>
               <p>Further, <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtle of the Lamb, deſcribing the nature and quality of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdom, ſaid, <hi>the wiſdom that is from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110312:13"/>above, is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be intreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, and without hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie,</hi> Jam. 3.17. Now no other wiſdom then this, was taught in the primitive Times, in Chriſtian Churches and Schools, while the purifying, and Victory giving Faith, was kept: the wiſdom of the world was Preached againſt as fooliſhneſs with God. Now whoever refuſes Wiſdom, Knowlege, and Underſtanding at the mouth of the Lord, ſuch learn Fooliſhneſs, Ignorance, Carnal wiſdom and wickedneſs at the mouth of the Serpent, and his wiſdom, nothing that's good proſpers under it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Riſe and Progreſs of Serpentine Wiſdom, that is the Wiſdom of this World.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Dam</hi> was Created a noble Plant, a bleſſed Diſciple, while obedient to the teaching of his Creatour, among many Pure, Heavenly, Sound, Savoury, and wholeſom leſſons, this was one; not to eat of, nor touch the forbidden Tree leſt they die. Now the Serpent filled with ſubtilty, laboured, firſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110312:13"/>to beget <hi>Eve</hi> into a queſtioning of the verity of Gods Heavenly Doctrine; ſaying, Yea, hath God ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall not eat of every Tree of the Garden,</hi> Secondly, the Serpent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly contradicted Gods Heavenly Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſaying, <hi>Ye ſhall not truly die.</hi> Thirdly, The Serpent informed <hi>Eve,</hi> that by touching and eating of that Tree, an advantage ſhould accrue thereby to them; <hi>Ye ſhall be as Gods, knowing good and evil,</hi> Gen. 3. the Serpent became prevalent, Gods teaching was rejected, the Serpents deadly Teachings and Inſinuations, Charms and Inchantments, were entertained, through this compliance; the Serpent got the Chair (as I may ſay) and became Teacher, than according to the Lords Heavenly word, death entered in upon them, even as a Conſumption ſeizes upon mans body gradually, in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the Serpent, a ſeed of enmity was ſown in mans heart, and from that ſeed ſprung another World, even a World of wickedneſs, ſavouring of the nature of the helliſh ſeedſman; <hi>Adam</hi> had never been driven out of the Paradiſe of bleſſedneſs but that through the Serpent being his Teacher, he learned <hi>to know good and evil,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius Agrippa</hi> of the vanity of Sciences.)</p>
               <p>While man kept his Station in the vertue of the ancient of days, he lived, moved, and had his being in him, he thought, ſpake,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110312:14"/>and acted in him; Yea, his thoughts, words, and actions, were the thoughts, words, and actions of God, in him and through him; here was a bleſſed Sabbath, Chriſt ſaid unto his Diſciples, travelling unto the pleaſant Valley of <hi>Adams</hi> Innocency; <hi>it is not ye that ſpeak, but the ſpirit of your Father which ſpeaketh in you,</hi> Matth. 10. yea, and <hi>Peter</hi> an Apoſtle of the Lamb, bare Record; ſaying, <hi>Holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.21. So that all the Holy Patriarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians, Children of Light, Children of the Day, who thought, ſpake and acted, in and through the vertue of the Lords pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in them; their Language was the Language of the Lord, 'tis ſo now of what Nation, Kingdom or Countrey ſoever ſuch be, yet they are living wirneſſes of that Language promiſed by the Lord, who ſaid, <hi>I will turn to the people a pure Language, that they may call upon the name of the Lord, to ſerve him with one conſent,</hi> Zeph. 3.9.</p>
               <p>In like manner <hi>Adam</hi> back-ſliden from the Lord, and complying with the old thoughts, words and works, from the miry lake of his power, and his poſterity cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in the gloomy region of the ſame, what proceeds from this helliſh conjunction, is the Language of the old Serpent, the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110312:14"/>of the beaſt, all wanton Poets, Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, Tragedians, painted Oratours, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Philoſophers are here found, thus of <hi>Bethel,</hi> that is, the Houſe of God, man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Bethaven,</hi> that is, a Houſe of iniquity and vanity.</p>
               <p>Thus the Serpent prevailing, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom increaſing, his helliſh Pills (as I may ſay) being ſwallowed, man was wrought out of his right courſe and diſpoſition, hence iſſued a numberleſs number of internal Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes.</p>
               <p>As in a corporal Impoſthume, purulent and foul matter is gathered together in ſome part of the body; ſo through joyning with the Serpent, purulent and foul matter of ſin, iniquity, tranſgreſſion, ſatanical Arts and Inventions are brought forth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Sons and Daughters of men are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed.</p>
               <p>As in an external Atrophy or Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the body through the want of due and convenient nutriment, by little and little pines way; ſo through complying with the Serpent, the mouth of faith came, and comes to be ſhut, which receives ſpiritual nouriſhment, which not being received, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual leanneſs ſtept, and ſtept in, yea a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Conſumption.</p>
               <p>As in a corporal Lethargie, there is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable propenſity to ſleepineſs, drowſineſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110312:15"/>and forgetfulneſs; ſo <hi>Adam</hi> not keeping his Heavenly Dominion in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aker, but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to the evil one, was thereby brought into a ſpiritual Lethargy into a ſleepy, drowſie, and forgetful ſtate this was <hi>Iſaraels</hi> which occaſioned the Lords complaint; <hi>my people have forgotten me days without number,</hi> Jer. 2.32.</p>
               <p>As through a depraved Appetite, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom nouriſhment is refuſed, nonconvenient, unprofitable, and Noxious things are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; even ſo the mind being carnalized Heavenly wiſdom, Bread of life, Water of life, Honey out of the Rock, the food of the ſoul is loathed, and ſpoiling Philoſophy, Satanical Arts, Parts and endowments; in a word, the wiſdom that is from below, is unſatiably ſought after.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> entring the barren Borders of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſm, from a Helliſh Lake, in the increaſe of that Kingdom, collected, guſhed out a mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſtream of Diabolical Arts, pernicious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and Artiſts; hence came he ungodly Aſtrologers, who from the obſervation of the Heavens, take upon them to foretel, what good or evil ſhall betide Men, States, Perſons, People, ſo to determine things of future contingence.</p>
               <p>Thence crawled out Charms, who uſe Verſes, Words, Ceremonies, Spells, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their deſired ends, as to heal, or hurt people, young or old.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:110312:15"/>
               <p>Hence crawled out Diviners, Wizards, who by a Diabolical Spirit take upon them to preſage or foretel things to come.</p>
               <p>Hence crawled out obſervers of Times, who ſuperſtitiouſly make difference of days and times, as good or bad, luckly or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky as they ſay, for the doing of ſuch a work, or undertaking a Journey, or appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing times for the doing of things.</p>
               <p>Hence crawled out the Conſulters of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Spirits, this was <hi>Sauls</hi> ſin, who ſought to a woman that had a Familiar Spirit; for which tranſgreſſion the Lord brought this heavy Judgment upon him.</p>
               <p>Hence crawled out Inchanters, who by obſerving the events of things, gather ſigns of good or evil, luck, (as they ſay) to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or others, and who by ſecret ſlights and juglings, deceive or delude the eye-ſight.</p>
               <p>Hence crawled out Witches, Sorcerers, having dealings with the Devil by compact or confedracy, changing any thing before the ſight, by a Diabolical power.</p>
               <p>Hence crawled out Necromancers, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the dead, or to the Devil in the form of the dead, making inquiry of the ſame, as <hi>Saul</hi> did.</p>
               <p>Hence crawled out the Magician, who through covenant with Satan is skild in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick Art.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:110312:16"/>
               <p>Hence ſprung in the Monthly Prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catours, taking upon them to foretell the occurrents of each Month.</p>
               <p>Hence crawled out Southſayers, who from the obſervation of the skie, or flight of Birds, take upon them to foretel things to come.</p>
               <p>Hence came in Stargazers, pretending knowledge of future events, by the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the courſes and conjunction of the Stars; theſe Artiſts were firſt found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Heathens, after crept into <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though expreſsly forbidden by the Lord, and are found alſo as it is ſaid, among the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>The Idolatrous <hi>Egyptians</hi> were great pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioners of Divination, who (as Writers affirm) firſt of all derived their Divination from the four Elements; ſome Divined from the obſervation of Fire; hence Pyromancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by the Air; hence Aero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by Water; hence Hydro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by the Earth; hence Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy.</p>
               <p>After this, wickedneſs and Satanical skill increaſing, a further progreſs was made; For,</p>
               <p>Some Divined by Fiſh; hence Icthuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:110312:16"/>
               <p>Some Divined by Herbs; hence Botano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by Figs; hence Sycomancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by Eggs; hence Oomancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by Rods; hence Rabdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy.</p>
               <p>Some by the crowing of Cocks; hence Alectrimancy.</p>
               <p>Some by She-goats; hence Aigemancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by Dreams; hence Oneiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by Inſenſe; hence Libano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy.</p>
               <p>Some by Water in a Baſon; hence Licano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by Smoak; hence Capno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by the Bay-tree; hence Daphnomancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by Wax; hence Ceromancy. Some by the lines of the Hands; hence Chiromancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by Sieve and Shears; hence Coſciomancy.</p>
               <p>This kind of Divination is (as 'tis ſaid) much in uſe now in the Northern parts, by the frequenters of Horſe Courſes and Foot Races.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by an Ax; hence Axino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined by Lots; hence Cleromancy.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:110312:17"/>
               <p>Some by the inſpection of Flour; hence Alphitomancy.</p>
               <p>Some Divined and gave anſwers out of their Bellies; hence Gaſtromancy. Some Divined by the obſervation of Birds, ſome by the entrails of Beaſts, ſome of theſe, (if not many,) are crept in among the profeſſors of Chriſtianity. <hi>Solomon</hi> knew what he ſaid, when he ſaid, <hi>God made man upright, but they have fought out many Inventions,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.</p>
               <p>From the very ſame ground iſſued in Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, Superſtition, damnable Hereſies, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Schiſms, ſtrong Deluſions, perverſe Diſputings, vagrant and wandring Deſires, fruitleſs Janglings, inconvenient Jeſtings, ſinful oppoſitions of Sciences, Inchanting Orations, feigned Purgatory, dreamed of by <hi>Plato</hi> the Philoſopher, and <hi>Virgil</hi> the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Poet, defended by many in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee the wiſdom of God being rejected, and the wiſdom of the old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and his Teaching being entertained, what Helliſh Artiſts and Arts, what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and unlawful Inventions, what ſtrange and ſoul-deſtroying Doctrines, are crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Stage of the World; what an Eclipſe is come upon the Sons and Daughters of men; but the Sun of righteouſneſs is riſen, and riſing with an effectual healing vertue, whereby the foggy exhaltation of ſin, ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110312:17"/>and tranſgreſſion of wicked Arts, and frivolous inventions, ſhall be ſcourged away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Riſe and Progreſs of Pagan Philoſophy, Worldly wiſdom crept in among the profeſsors of Christianity, and Testimonies of the Holy men of God against the ſame.</head>
               <p>Pagans of ſeveral Nations, deſirous of wiſdom, to ſome ſtraps of <hi>Moſes</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to Morals, Naturals and Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turals, added the corrupt ingredients of their own Inventions and imaginations; ſo patch up their Ethicks, Phyſicks, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſicks, ſo triumphed in the ſplendor of their wiſdom, and gained great eſteem thorough the ſame, and were (as I may ſay) pointed at by the fingers of others, and were called <hi>Magi,</hi> that is, wiſemen, whatſoever (ſaith <hi>Andrew Sympſon</hi>) <hi>Orpheus Homer, Solon, Pythagoras, Plato,</hi> and other Grecians, Philoſophers, Poets, Hiſtorians, have left in Record, concerning God and Divine things, they took all out of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110312:18"/>Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> whereunto they added the intermixture of their own Inventions and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aginations, depraved and wreſted the ſame, <hi>Auguſt. de Civit. Dei,</hi> to ſay the beſt Rabbins, and Philoſophers ſaith <hi>Trap; ſunt bona miſta malis, ſunt mala mista bonis,</hi> that is to ſay in them, good is mixed with evil, and evil with good.</p>
               <p>The Greeks through this py-bal wiſdom were called Sophoi, that is, wiſemen; now <hi>Pythagoras</hi> refuſed that Title as too ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and peculiar to <hi>Ens Entium,</hi> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of beings, God alone, and in way of modeſty he called himſelf <hi>Philoſophos,</hi> that is, a Lover of wiſdom; which Title <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Plato</hi> and others aſſumed, in imitation of theſe Greeks, the Romans called ſuch <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and imitation of the Romans; in the Engliſh <hi>Orthography,</hi> ſuch are called Philoſophers, that is, Lover of wiſdom; hence came the Philoſophy of the <hi>Egyptians, Phenicians, Caldeans, Phrygians, Lybians, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopians, Scithians, Thracians, Perſians, Indians, Brachmans, Spaniards, Italians, Greeks, Druides,</hi> of <hi>Pythagoras, Socrates, Plato, Aristotle,</hi> of the <hi>Cynicks, Stoicks, Scepticks, Epicureans;</hi> theſe ſay, and many others, received their Philoſophy; from the writings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> by them depraved and wreſted, adding the dregs of their own opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, inventions and imaginations they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110312:18"/>received of theſe things alſo, one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
               <p>And of the agreement or rather diſagre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Pagan Philoſophers among themſelves, Writers are not ſilent, for not being content with Logomachy, that is, Verbal altercation; they fell at length to Dagger drawing one againſt another, <hi>Johan. Franc. Pic. Mizand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the abſurd opinions of Pagan Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, as of their Magicks South ſayings, Conjurings, caſting of Nativities, their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the worlds Eternity, of the Souls Mortality, of the tranſmigration of the Soul from one body into another, of like tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament and quality, I forbear further to particulariſe.</p>
               <p>How Pagan Philoſophy. Arts and Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, called Hand-maids to Divinity, have been and are courted, embraced and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Heavenly wiſdom, the Miſtreſs, hath been and is ſleighted, <hi>the wiſe in heart under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand:</hi> the Egyptians (ſaith <hi>Theophilus Gales</hi>) ſo purſued the ſtudy of the Mathematicks, that the Title of Prophet, Prieſt, or wiſeman, was allowed to none, but ſuch as were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly inſtructed therein before. Now how ſpoiling Philoſophy, Tongues, Ethnick Arts, natural endowments and qualifications, are doted upon among the Profeſſors of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity is evident, in that, who without
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110312:19"/>qualifications are fitted by the Lord, for the work of the Miniſtry, they are branded as Hereticks, and perſecuted.</p>
               <p>It was a ſaying of <hi>Solomon, Take away the droſs from the Silver, and there ſhall come forth a Veſſel for the finer,</hi> Pro. 25.4. Now if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intermixture of Paganiſm, ſpoiling Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, Satanical Arts; in a word, the wiſdom of the fleſh, which is fooliſhneſs, with God, were ſcoured away, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdom in its primitive purity in Schools and Churches were reſtored; happy would the Nations be, which in meaſure was attempted; for in the School of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> an Eclecktick Sect flouriſhed, ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it Selected and picked out the choice parts of Philoſophy, out of all Sects, this laudable attempt was undertaken by men accounted eminent, <hi>Potamon, Plutarch, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monius</hi> and other Philoſophers, with what iſſue and ſucceſs a concluſion may be drawn, for that ſomuch of the droſs of Satanical Art, carnal reaſon, inventions and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation remains, as that it yet remains, ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Philoſophy; <hi>Corruptio optimi fit peſſima,</hi> that is, beſt things corrupted, become the worſt. <hi>Theophilus Gale</hi> adviſes well that all the placets, or opinions of Philoſophers, ſhould be brought to be tryed by the holy Scriptures, that there it may appear, what ſhould be imbraced, and what ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:110312:19"/>
               <p>Man in the beauty of his Innocency was to eye the Lord, and in his Spirit, the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, the products of the Lords power and wiſdom, for all ſerious, ſolid, ſound and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable knowledge, relates to the eſſentiality of God, and to the Creation, the products of his power, and to uſeful and neceſſary concerns; herein appears true wiſdom, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Philoſophy: <hi>Plato</hi> though an Ethnick, through a Divine ſpark, or through the writings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> in that ſpark bouldly and truly called, the knowledge of God, the true Philoſophy, how (ſaith <hi>Epinomondas</hi>) can God be the Author of all good, if he be not the Authour of the chiefeſt good, that is, wiſdom.</p>
               <p>The Serpent being prevalent, disjoynted, diſlocated; that is, wreſted man out of his bleſſed State, and center'd him in his own power, whence iſſued into the world, a mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſtream of earthly wiſdom, inventions, and Idolatry; the poſterity of <hi>Noah,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Theophilus Gale</hi>) degenerating from the pure Philoſophy, that is, wiſdom of the Patriarchs, plunged into the bottomleſs pit, of diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Aſtrology, and Idolatry; for in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of Coeleſtial bodies, the feeling of the Creatour being loſt, they were firſt of all hurried to the admiration of them, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the adoration of them; ſo thoſe glorious Creatures being lifted up into the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110312:20"/>throne of the Creatour, became the object of monſtrous Idolatry, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Job.</hi> 31.26, 27.</p>
               <p>Geographers affirm that the Valley in which <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> were built, was full of ſaltiſh and bituminous pits; the Lake <hi>Aſphaltites,</hi> called alſo, <hi>Mare Mortuum</hi> that is, the dead Sea, becauſe the very Fiſh cannot live in its foul groſs waters, yea; anp Birds flying over it were ſmothered and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by its exhalations: <hi>Adam</hi> as Created of the Lord, was a fruitful Valley, plentious, infragrant, odoriferous, aromatical, balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical fruits, ſhewing forth the regency of the Lambs life in him, cloſing with the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whiſpers of the Serpent, a muddy Lake (as I may ſay) guſhed into the world, whoſe exhalations are pernicious, this may ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually be called the dead Sea; none can live to God, to righteouſneſs, in that which the Devil brings in, in the putred or rotten ſtock old <hi>Adam,</hi> all die, in Chriſt is life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> We read Philoſophers, becauſe many good moral ſayings are in them, and we learn natural Arts to qualifie and enable us, for the underſtanding of Heavenly things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 'Tis recorded in Scripture, <hi>that Chriſt is the true light, that lighteth every man that cometh into the world,</hi> Joh. 1.9. Pagan Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, as well as others, I (ſaid <hi>Du Hamel</hi>) aſcent unto the Platoniſts, that mens
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110312:20"/>minds are enlightened with a Divine light; ſo every man hath in himſelf the ground of morality, which man turning from within, and fetching in from without, he continues in Clouds of darkneſs, and an Eclipſe in the world of his heart, what the Philoſophers ſpoke from that, is found and good, but through a now perſeverance in it, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtures entred in, and what proceeded from the mind thus carnalized, was ſpoiling Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy; <hi>Corruptio optimi fit peſſima,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; yea, and the ſame <hi>John</hi> bare Record, ſaying, <hi>the light ſhined in darkneſs and the darkneſs comprehended it not,</hi> John. 1.5. this non-comprehenſion of Pagan Philoſophers, as well as of others, ſo far prevailed, that they could in no wiſe comprehend the ſparks of Divine light, which ſhined in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their hearts, but unjuſtly, and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, reſiſted, reſtrained, and oppoſed the ſame, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18, 19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And natural Arts, Parts, Endowments, Languages, Accompliſhments, cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal the knowledge of Heavenly things; <hi>Canſt thou</hi> (ſaid <hi>Zophar</hi>) <hi>by ſearching find out God?</hi> Job. 11.7, <hi>&amp;c. No man knows the Father ſave the Son, and he to whom the Son reveals him,</hi> Matth. 11.27. and <hi>Paul,</hi> who was eminent in Tongues, natural in Parts and Abilities, and knew what Key opened into the rich Cabinet of Heavenly wiſdom,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110312:21"/>and Treaſures, he excluded natural Arts, and Parts to be that Key; ſaying expreſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>the natural man receives not the things of the ſpirit of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. God and the things of God, are known in and by the ſpirit, this ſpirit <hi>Paul</hi> Preaches up, not natural Arts, Parts, and Tongues; <hi>Plato</hi> a Heathen Philoſopher, ſaid well, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is not acquired but infuſed of God, a natural man though he have mounted to the Turret of Philoſophick elevations, and may profeſs himſelf to be a great Sophiſt, that is, wiſeman; yet he is ignorant of the ſaving knowledge of the Lord, which only comes by the teaching of the Lord, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Acts.</hi> 17.18, 23.1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</p>
               <p>Holy men of God, inſpired of God, taught of God, repleniſhed with the vertue, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, and ſweetneſs, of Heavenly wiſdom, in the Patriarchal, Moſaical, and Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal diſpenſations, juſtified the ſame, and in it, by it, and through it, grew in clearneſs of underſtanding, diſtinguiſhing perſons, ſo bare Teſtimoy againſt the old Serpent, and all his products, his ſpoiling Philoſophy, wiſdom of the fleſh, introduced into the world, by thoſe lying lips, that ſeduced <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> from their bleſſed being and welbeing in the Lord.</p>
               <p>Certain Philoſophers of the <hi>Epicureans</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:110312:21"/>and of the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> in wiſdom of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, encountred <hi>Paul,</hi> who was partaker of Divine wiſdom, and called him a babler, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.18. and how the Divine wiſdom revealed in the lovers of ſimplicity, is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by Philoſophers now; this Nation and others afford many examples, yet the wiſdom of the living God, who are of God, cannot but contend for, the pure wiſdom of the rock of Ages; who ſaid, <hi>Heaven is my Throne, and Earth is my Foot ſtool,</hi> Act. 7.49. there are as Schools diſtinguiſh, <hi>Bona throni;</hi> the Treaſures of Heaven, Chriſt the repoſitory of pure, ſou-Iſaving, ſoul-refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, life-giving wiſdom, and knowledge, and there are <hi>Bona Scabelli,</hi> that is, the fruits and riches of the Earth; now the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and deportment of multitudes is ſuch, that their very life ſpeaks, that <hi>Earth is their Throne, and Heaven their Foot-ſtool;</hi> hot in the purſuit of the Earth, the pleaſures and delights thereof, ſlighting the pearl of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdom; the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> ſaid, he had ſo much to do on Earth, that he had no time to look after Heaven: <hi>Trapp</hi> ſaith, the frame of the ſpirits of men, beſpeaks them to be thus minded, complying rather with the Divinity of <hi>Sardanapalus, Ede, bibe, lude, post mortem nulla voluptas,</hi> then with the Doctrine of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>learn of me:</hi> the beforem-entioned <hi>Epicureans,</hi> were a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110312:22"/>Sect of Philoſophers, ſo called from <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> who was born in <hi>Athens,</hi> and lived in the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, <hi>Ptolomy, Lagus</hi> and <hi>Philadelphus,</hi> he held that the world came of the Atomes, or Motes in the Sun, that the Souls dye with the Bodies, that there is no providence, that worldly pleaſure is the <hi>Summum bonum,</hi> the chiefeſt good; theſe with others, Philoſophers reſiſted <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the beloved of God, in <hi>Rome</hi> called to be Saints, bare this Record, relating to the wiſdom of the fleſh, and to the wiſdom of the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.6. to be carnally minded is death, which being truly tranſlated is thus, the wiſdom, deſire, or mind of the fleſh is death; but the wiſdom, deſire, or mind of the ſpirit, is life, and peace; the wiſdom of the fleſh is death, and is not ſpoiling Philoſophy, laſcivious Poems, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, Tragedies, frivolous Fables, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanting Orations, the Subject taught in Schools and Colledges of the wiſdom of the fleſh; I ſay yes, and that they are death, and tend to Bind and Fetter Men in Chains of darkneſs, in the Dungeon of death, but the wiſdom of the ſpirit gives the ſimple a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence in the fragrant Chamber of life and peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> further Teſtified to the Sanctified at <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſaying, Chriſt ſent me not to baptize,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110312:22"/>but to preach the Goſpel, not with wiſdom words, leaſt the Croſs of Chriſt ſhould be made of none effect; for it is written, <hi>I will destroy the wiſdom of the wiſe:</hi> Here the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents wiſdom, affected eloquence, pompous and painted ſpeech, attained by ſatanical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, orhumane acquiſition, by Study, peruſal of Heathen Authors, is decryed, not wiſdom of words, (ſaith he (leaſt the Croſs of Chriſt, the door through which pure, Divine, Heavenly wiſdom enters the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of mans heart, ſhould be made of none effect; Further ſaith he, the world by wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom knew not God, neither doth the world by its wiſdom now know God; to what purpoſe then are Youth and others ſo toiled, for the attainment of that, which is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the account of God, and brings not to his knowledge, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17, 19, 20.</p>
               <p>Again, this clear-ſighted Apoſtle of the Lamb, through Divine eye-ſalve, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing between the grounds, natures and effects, of the wiſdom from above, and the wiſdom from below; ſaith on this wiſe, <hi>We ſpeak wiſdom among them that are perfect, yet not the wiſdom of this world, nor of the Princes of this world, that come to nought; but we ſpeak the wiſdom of God in a Myſtery, which none of the Princes of this world knew; for had they known it, they would not have crucified the Lord of Glory: which things alſo we ſpeak,</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110312:23"/>he) <hi>not in the words which mans wiſdom teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but which the Holy Spirit teacheth,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.6, 7, 8, 13. Further he ſaith, <hi>the Natural man knows not the things of the ſpirit of God, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 14. The Natural man though mounted to the very Zenith of Philoſophick notions, and ſtored with the quinteſſence of fleſhes wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs, which in very deed is wickedneſs, filled as a well loaded Veſſel, with acquired Arts, and Parts; yet being a natural man, darkened with the ſmoak of carnal wiſdom, in that State he cannot receive the wiſdom which is from above; in his eye it is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the world and its wiſdom is a pearl in his eye, the harmleſs Dove of Heavenly wiſdom enters in at another window, the Croſs of Chriſt, fooliſhneſs to them that periſh.</p>
               <p>Further, the faithful Embaſſador, and true witneſs <hi>Paul,</hi> in the wiſdom of God bare Record, againſt the wiſdom of the world; ſaying, <hi>The wiſdom of this world is fooliſhneſs with God,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.19 <hi>Adam</hi> in the wiſdom of God, knew God, and the Creation; Now the Serpent by his inſinuations; working man into a compliance with his will, brought in a Sea of iniquity and confuſion, a world of unrighteouſneſs, and a wiſdom favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Nature, now ſpoiling Philoſophy,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110312:23"/>Inchanting Orations, wanton Poems, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, Tragedies, Fables, are a part of of his wiſdom, taught in Schools and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, ſo is fooliſhneſs with God, though highly eſteemed among men; <hi>yet are they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination in the ſight of God,</hi> Luke 16.15. I am brought into the credence of this, that as the rays of the Sun of righteouſneſs are diſplayed in man, as Heavenly wiſdom is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, as Nations become ſeaſoned with the ſalt of the Kingdom, theſe abominations will become burdenſom; yea and rejected as a Menſtrous Cloath; then ſhall Compoſers, Printers, Correctors, Stichers, Binders, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, School-Maſters, Tutors, in Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, that have Traded in this dead Sea, dregs of Sataniſm, turn from their unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful concerns, as the evil thereof is diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and juſtifie the wiſdom that is from above.</p>
               <p>Further, this faithful Steward <hi>Paul,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Saints and faithful Brethren at <hi>Colloſſe,</hi> exhorted them, ſaying, <hi>Beware leaſt any man ſpoil you through Philoſophy and vain deceipt, after the tradition of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after Chriſt,</hi> Coloſ 2.8. thus who keep not in Chriſt, the wiſdom of the Father, but lend an ear to the Pagan Philoſophick notions of falſe teachers, they are led by them out of the right path, bound and Captives; thus <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:110312:24"/>in the wiſdom from above, cautions them to beware of wiſdom from below.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Paul</hi> writing to <hi>Timothy</hi> his own Son in the Faith, exhortshim, to charge ſome, <hi>not to give heed to Fables, and endleſs genealogies, which miniſter questions, rather then godly edyfying, which is faith,</hi> 1. Tim. 1.3, 4. Now what a muddy ſtream of Fables and fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Poems, Comedies, and Tragedies, are guſhed into Chriſtian Schools, how the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous Pedegrees of the Heathens Gods, are (as I may ſay) driven by force of Arms into tender youth, hopeful, if not depraved and corrupted by Ethnick education, I leave to the wiſe in heart to Judge, who have known theſe things and the burden of them; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſaith to <hi>Timothy, refuſe prophane and old wives Fables, and exerciſe thy ſelf unto god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.7.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> writing to the twelve Tribes, ſcattered abroad, draws his Sword (as I may ſay) againſt Serpentine wiſdom, ſaying, <hi>if ye have bitter envying, and ſtrife in your hearts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This wiſdom deſcends not from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, deviliſh,</hi> James 1.14, 15. Mark, earthly, ſenſual, deviliſh, O that Chriſtendom would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this, in whom the helliſh ſpark hath not only kindled them into ſtrife and envy, but to be as a prey to the mouth of the Sword; Chriſtendom is become as <hi>Golgotha,</hi> a place
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110312:24"/>of Skulls, as <hi>Aceldama,</hi> the Field of Blood; the Apoſtle writing to the Church, ſaid, <hi>ye are taught of God to love one another,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4. Now where ſtrife, envy, and bloodſhed is, of whom are they taught? even of the Serpent, who was a Murderer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, the Author of that wiſdom, which is earthly, ſenſual and deviliſh, a true Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of that wiſdom which is from below; it is called earthly, becauſe it ariſes from the earth, keeps man in an unregenerate ſtate, out of Heavenly mindedneſs, wholly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning man for earthly ends, ſenſual, as wholly concerned in the purſuit of carnal, ſinful and tranſient pleaſures, deviliſh, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by him, doing his work, and brings to his end, wiſdom from above Reſcues from his tyranny.</p>
               <p>In the Apoſtles days, ſuch as knew the Lords call into the Miniſtry, they were Stars in Heaven, ſetlted in Heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus, they had the Heavenly Key, which opened to them the Royal Cabinet of Heavenly Treaſures, they received no wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in Church or School, but what was Heavenly; but a Star being faln to the earth; Mark this, to the earth, then an earthly Key was thruſt into the hand, even the Key of the bottomleſs Pit; then aroſe a Smoak Which darkned the Sun and the Air, what is this Smoak? even Serpentine wiſdom which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110312:25"/>ſteamed into Churches and Schools, the gradual riſe of this, ſpoiled the glory and beauty of Primitive Chriſtianity; at this door crept into the Church Traditions, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſics, Scyſms, Doctrinal errours, Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Idolatry, Pardons, Indulgences, Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, Soul-maſſes, Dirgies, Purgatory, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonization of Saints; In a word, deviliſh errors were ſet a broach, <hi>Mabomet</hi> ſteamed out his <hi>Alcoran</hi> for Divine Scriptures, into Schools ſteamed alſo in ſpoiling Philoſophy, bewitching Orations, pompous and painted Rhetorick, laſcivious Poems, vain Comedies, fooliſh Tragedies, frivilous Fables, Pagan Ethicks, Phyſicks and Metaphyſicks, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Youth is corrupted, as the Sea Monſter called <hi>Phyſeter,</hi> as naturaliſts write, mounts above the tops of Ships, ſtanding upright in the Sea, like a Pillar, and ſpouts out great flouds of water, whereby it overwhelms or indangers them; ſo upon the fall of the Star from Heaven, the Sea-Monſter Satan, got up into the Church and, ſpouted out great flouds of errors, falſe Doctrines, and of earthly wiſdom into Schools and Churches, whereby they ſunk down into the depth of ignorance, ſpiritual blindneſs, Idolatry and corruption, but Heavenly wiſdom is diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its power, vertue and influence, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine wiſdom, be it in Church or School, muſt be ſcoured away.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:110312:25"/>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> A rehearſal of Testimonies, born by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral men eminent in the Church, ſince the Apostles days, against Heathen learning, or the teaching of it, in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Schools, as alſo of others.</head>
               <p>By what hath been ſpoken 'tis evident, that the holy men of God, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all to be inſpired of God, bare ſound Record and a living Teſtimony in the wiſdom of God, againſt the wiſdom of the Serpent, the wiſdom of the World; many alſo who have lived ſince the Apoſtles days, yea and ſince the fall of the Star from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in the gloomy night of Apoſtaſie, in that meaſure of Heavenly wiſdom then made known, have born Teſtimony againſt teaching Heathen Authors, ſpoiling Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, wanton Poets in Chriſtian Schools or Colledges; Yea, and have ſpoken freely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Univerſities defiled with the ſame, in confirmation of this aſſertion a few Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are preſented to the conſideration of the Reader.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> brings in <hi>Plato,</hi> ſharply blaming that firſt Education, as deſtructive, which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110312:26"/>was uſed by the Greeks, in reading the feigned Comical and Tragical inventions of Poets, <hi>Cap.</hi> 49. <hi>p.</hi> 618.</p>
               <p>As far as I can gather from the writings of the Ancients, Philoſophy is very hurtful unto him that is much addicted to the ſtudy, thereof, <hi>Joh. Pic. Mirand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the diſcord of Divines, hath proceeded from Philoſophers, for as much as Divines in later Ages, have mixed the muddy water of Philoſophers with the living vein of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oracles, <hi>Joh. Pic. Mirand.</hi> that is, have mixed Heathen Philoſophick Notions, with the Scriptures of truth: It is known by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memtable experience, how dangerous a thing it is, to be exerciſed in the writings of Ethnick Philoſophers, and how eaſily the plague of lies, and vanity creeps through the ſame into mens minds <hi>Theo. Gale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the times of the <hi>Haſmoneans,</hi> this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creee made, let him be accurſed, who teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Son the Philoſophy of the Greeks, <hi>Theo. Gale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What but Greek Philoſophy, was the firſt Seminary or ſeed-Plot of principle Errors, in the Churches in the Apoſtles days, and in Churches immediately ſucceeding. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Tertullian</hi> called Philoſophers the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs of Hereticks, <hi>The. Gale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not hard to ſhew (ſaith the ſame Authour) that the whole Myſtery of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110312:26"/>and the whole Syſtem of Antichriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, which hath moleſted the Chriſtian Church, for ſo many Centuries, ought to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe their riſe and progreſs to Heathen Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy.</p>
               <p>There are (ſaith <hi>Andrew Sympſon</hi>) who ſpend much precious time upon vile Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, curious Arts, prophane Stories; laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Poems, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moſt of the Hereſies that have been in the Church, have come in by Learned men, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then by Ignorant men. <hi>Ed. Calamy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jerome</hi> a Father of the Church, who lived about the year 384. reading the Book of <hi>Cicero,</hi> was (as 'tis ſaid) rebuked by an Angel, becauſe that he being a Chriſtian, minded the Fictions of the Gentiles. <hi>Jacobus Laurentius de libr. Gentil. pag.</hi> 41.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gratian</hi> put out a Canon, that a Biſhop ſhould not read Heathen Books. <hi>Jac. Laur. pag.</hi> 41.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great (ſaith <hi>Jac. Laurentius de libris Gentilium</hi>) forbad all Biſhops the reading of Heathen Books. <hi>pag.</hi> 41.</p>
               <p>Pernicious Books are to be burned, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard is to be given to the price of them. <hi>Piſcat.</hi> on <hi>Acts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the wiſdom of a man is in this one thing, that he know and worſhip Chriſt. <hi>Lactant. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian</hi> the chief Lawyer, <hi>Galen</hi> the chief
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110312:27"/>Phyſician, <hi>Porphiry</hi> the chiefeſt <hi>Ariſtotelian, Plotinus</hi> the chiefeſt <hi>Platonist,</hi> were profeſs'd enemies to Chriſt, and his Truth. <hi>Trapp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtin</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hippo</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> about the year 399. ſaid, the unlearned take Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by force, but we with our learning are thruſt into Hell.</p>
               <p>It repented <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> that when he was young, he had preached more to pleaſe, then to profit others.</p>
               <p>Neither the <hi>Jews</hi> by their profound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, nor the <hi>Gentiles</hi> by their Wits and Wizards, could grope out God. <hi>Trapp</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Greeks</hi> ſought after wiſdom, <hi>viz.</hi> of this World, ſo ſhut out Heavenly wiſdom; <hi>Intus existens prohibet alienum,</hi> they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained not what they ſought. <hi>Trapp</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22.</p>
               <p>We that have obtained the knowledge of God, by and through his Grace, are far more Wiſe and more bleſſed then <hi>Plato, Ariſtotle, &amp;c. Piſcat.</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>In a natural man there is an impotency, that is, want of power to know and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſpiritual things. <hi>Piſcat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wiſdom that is of the Fleſh, ſerves the Worldling (as the Oſtrich wings) to make him out-run others upon Earth, and in Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, but helps him never a whit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven. <hi>Trapp</hi> on the <hi>Corinth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:110312:27"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Emperor ſuſpecting <hi>Julian</hi>'s proneneſs to Paganiſm, ſent him to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully grounded in Chriſtianity to <hi>Nicome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia;</hi> but he frequented by ſtealth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Libanius</hi> and <hi>Iamblichus,</hi> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, who warped him wholly to their bent, which brake out afterwards. <hi>Trapp</hi> on <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>In the year 220. the <hi>Artemonites,</hi> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain kind of Hereticks, corrupted Scripture out of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Theophraſtus,</hi> turning all into Queſtions, as afterwards School-men did, that evil generation of Dunghill Divines, as one calleth them. <hi>Trapp</hi> on <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Gentiles</hi> could not be ſaved by their Philoſophy, without Chriſt; and yet not only the Divines of <hi>Cullen,</hi> ſet forth a Book concerning the Salvation of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> whom they called Chriſt's forerunner in Naturals, as <hi>John Baptist</hi> was in Supernaturals; but alſo ſome of the School Doctors, grave men (ſaith <hi>Acoſta</hi>) do promiſe men Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without the knowledge of Chriſt. <hi>Trapp</hi> on <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.8.</p>
               <p>The Moral Philoſophy of prophane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, treating of the chiefeſt good, and of the happineſs of man, and of virtue, is no other thing then vain deceit. <hi>Piſc. Coloſ.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Seeing we are complete in Chriſt, they commit folly who have recourſe unto pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Philoſophers.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:110312:28"/>
               <p>The deep Theorems of Philoſophy (ſaid King <hi>James</hi>) make one learned, but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom better; and oftentimes worſe, meer Atheiſts. There is an <hi>Arabick</hi> Proverb, <hi>Cum errat eruditus, errat errore erudito;</hi> that is, a learned man hath learned errors. <hi>Trapp</hi> on <hi>Acts</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> wrote many things moſt abſurd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning God, as that he is a living Creature, that he works not freely, but by a kind of ſervile neceſſity; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he deſerves no praiſe, ſith he doth but what he muſt do: yet at <hi>Stuckard</hi> in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> was found a Doctor of Divinity, that preached to the people, that the Church might be ſufficiently well taught and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Philoſophy, eſpecially his Ethicks <hi>Trapp</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21.</p>
               <p>To uſe Heathen Authors for oftentation, is to make a Calf of the Treaſures gotten out of <hi>Egypt. Trapp</hi> of Arts.</p>
               <p>Many (ſaith one) through their love to the Tree of Knowledge, loſe the Tree of Life.</p>
               <p>Papiſts ſay, that we may find their Holy-Water, and ſprinkling of Sepulchres, in <hi>Juve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi>'s ſixth Satyr; their Lights in Sepulchres, in <hi>Suetonius</hi> his <hi>Octavius;</hi> Lamps lighted on Saturdays, in <hi>Seneca</hi>'s 96 Epiſtle; diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Tapers among the people, in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crobius</hi> his Saturnals; Purgatory, in <hi>Virgil</hi>'s
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110312:28"/>
                  <hi>Aeneids<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Trapp.</hi> Thus proving their Doctrines by Heathen Authors, not by Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Averroes</hi> an <hi>Arabian</hi> Phyſician, ſo madly admired his Maſter <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> as that he ſaid, there was no errour to be found in his Works, that his Learning was the chief Truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When he dyed, he cryed out, <hi>Sit anima mea cum Philoſophis,</hi> Let my Soul be, where the Philoſophers Souls are. <hi>Trapp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> tells us, that he left his Gentiliſm upon reading a piece of <hi>Plato. Trapp</hi> of Arts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtin</hi> acknowledgeth, that nothing more cooled his affections towards that Book called <hi>Cicero</hi>'s <hi>Hortenſius,</hi> then that he found not the name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in it; and that on this confideration he was perſwaded to the love of Heavenly wiſdom, and contemplation of things above. <hi>Trapp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The knowledge of Chriſt is the only Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, without which all other Learning, doth but light men into utter darkneſs. <hi>Trapp</hi> of Arts.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Divinity, which he calls his Metaphyſicks, whereof he wrote 14 Books, it is (ſaith <hi>Ramus</hi>) the moſt fooliſh and impious piece of Sophiſtry, that ever was written. <hi>Trapp</hi> of Arts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lotamus Lovanienſis</hi> wrote, that there was no other Faith found in <hi>Abraham,</hi> then was found in <hi>Cicero</hi> a Heathen Philoſopher:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110312:29"/>whereas <hi>Abram</hi> ſaw my day (ſaith Chriſt) and rejoyced, he walked with God, and was upright; it was not thus with <hi>Cicero. Trapp</hi> of Arts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Latimer</hi> was ſo wrought upon by <hi>Bilney</hi>'s confeſſion, as that he began to ſmell the Word of God, and to forſake School Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and ſuch like fooleries, and horrible barbariſm, which had overſpread the eye of whole Chriſtendom. <hi>Trapp</hi> of Arts.</p>
               <p>The dignity and ſtudy of <hi>Latine, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> the Holy Spirit ſeems to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate their continuance in the Church, by the Inſcription of Chriſt's Title on the Croſs in thoſe three Tongues, and the utter era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating of all frivolous and fruitleſs School Quirks, Monkiſh Dotages, Legendary Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. <hi>Trapp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> one time baniſhed all Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers out of their City. <hi>Gel. lib.</hi> 15. <hi>Trapp</hi> of Arts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Licinius</hi> the Emperor called Heathen Learning, the plague and poyſon of the Commonwealth. <hi>Trapp</hi> of Arts.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the ſecond, pronounced all Scholars Hereticks, and ſeriouſly exhorted the <hi>Romans,</hi> not to breed up their Children at School, ſaying, it was enough if they could read and write. <hi>Trapp</hi> of Arts.</p>
               <p>The Heathen <hi>Romans</hi> having conquer'd this Nation, and inhabiting in it for 500
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:110312:29"/>years, as Hiſtories inform us, they erected Schools in this Nation to teach the <hi>Britains,</hi> and brought in their Heathen Poets, Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Tragedies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into Schools, which to the ſhame and corrupting of the Nation are yet continued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Julius Agricola,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor's Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant in <hi>Britain,</hi> taught the <hi>Britains</hi> civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and prevailed with Noblemen to breed up their Sons in liberal Arts, and brought them to affect the <hi>Roman</hi> Eloquence; then they began to imitate the <hi>Roman</hi> Faſhions, the Gown, proud Buildings, Baths, and Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetings, which the fooliſher ſort called Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility, but was indeed a ſecret Art to prepare them for bondage. <hi>Milton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edgar</hi> a <hi>Saxon</hi> King, put forth a Canon, that on Feſtival days every one ſhould ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from prophane Heathen Songs, and from diabolical Games and Paſtimes.</p>
               <p>Further he enjoyned, that every one ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from the reading of fabulous and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd things, and from filthy and blaſphemous Ballads: Not well obſerved now.</p>
               <p>I <hi>Martin Luther</hi> give notice to all, that on <hi>Monday, &amp;c.</hi> all the Books of the Pope be burned, and of ſome of his Diſciples. He gives a reaſon of this thing, ſaying that they are miſchievous, falſe, ſeducing, wicked, <hi>&amp;c. Luth. Tom.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> ſpeaking of Popiſh Schools and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:110312:30"/>Monaſteries, ſaid, This is my mind and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that theſe Stables of two-footed Aſſes, and Schools of the Devil, ſhould be levelled with the ground, or changed into Chriſtian Schools, by a Godly transformation. <hi>Luth. de inſtitutione puerorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heathen Learning (ſaith <hi>Gell</hi>) hath a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing and a bewitching beauty; <hi>capta, capit,</hi> being taken, it is much taking alſo, and wins much upon mens affections: and great danger there is (ſaith he) leſt men court the Handmaid, rather then the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs; Earthly, inſtead of Heavenly wiſdom, to their deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Eſſential inward knowledge in the ſecret underſtanding, is not from fleſh and bloud, nor from the multitude of Books, but by a paſſive reception of Divine things; not by ſtudy, but by patience and ſubmiſſion. <hi>Oſw. Crollius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Academical Spirit cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the myſtery of intrinſical Teaching, only humility is capable of illumination. <hi>Oſw. Croll.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Schools of the Gentiles have had their time, wherein they have become vain in their imaginations, being exerciſed in vain Philoſophy, and oppoſition of Science, falſly ſo called, whereof the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> admoniſhed true Chriſtians, to take heed they were not deceived by it. Thus ſaith
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:110312:30"/>the Tranſlator of <hi>John Baptiſta Van Helmont</hi>'s Phyſick Refined, in his Premonition to the Candid Reader.</p>
               <p>Further, ſaith he, the Wiſe men of the Eaſt by the direction of the Star, came to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Child, laying down all their wiſdom at his feet; for a lively token, that all true wiſdom was to be received from him, in whom all the treaſures of wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge dwells.</p>
               <p>Further, ſaith he, ſuch hath been the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of the fleſhly Serpent, that under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of owning the name of Chriſt, he hath taken up Paganiſh means and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to build withall, calling the dregs and droſs of Heathen Schools, Handmaids of Divinity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Baptista Van Helmont</hi> in his Phyſick Refined, ſaid, Logick is ſo far from leading to the knowledge of Univerſals, that it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thruſts men down into errors.</p>
               <p>The World (ſaith this <hi>Helmont</hi>) hath ſuffer'd it ſelf to be circumvented by <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> who boaſted of Logick to be the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Sciences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aristotle</hi> (ſaith this <hi>Helmont</hi>) extolled the method of Diſputing invented by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and he takes away all knowledge from a man, unleſs he hath yielded himſelf to be inſtructed in Logick.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jerom</hi> (on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and 143.) doth not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:110312:31"/>unworthily compare the Art of Syllogizing to the Plagues of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and he calls Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical demonſtrations, Dog-like diſcourſes. <hi>Helmont.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Schools (ſaith this <hi>Helmont</hi>) ſuppoſing Logick as neceſſary, do oppoſe themſelves to the commands of the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>I wonder (ſaith <hi>Helmont</hi>) at the great blindneſs of Schools, in ſo great magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Logick.</p>
               <p>Let Schools (ſaith <hi>Helmont</hi>) tell me, what Science Logick hath ever brought to light, whether Geometry, making of Glaſs, Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Husbandry, Medicine, conducting of Water, of Minerals, of Arithmetick, of Building, or any profitable Science; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily none.</p>
               <p>Schools of Logick (ſaith this <hi>Helmont</hi>) muſt needs confeſs, that through boaſting, deceit, and ignorance, it hath deceived the credulous World.</p>
               <p>To ſay that Logical diſcourſe is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for Divines, to refute the ſubtilties of Hereſies, that thing (ſaith this <hi>Helmont</hi>) would be to be wiſe above the Apoſtle, and to commend the abuſes of Schools, above the Holy Scriptures; this were to dethrone Goſpel-weapons, and to inthrone Paganiſm <hi>Steven</hi> by the Sword of the Spirit, and by Heavenly wiſdom, refuted the <hi>Libertines, Cyrenians, Alexandrians, Cilicians,</hi> not by
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:110312:31"/>Pagan Logick, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.9, 10. Chriſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>I will give you a mouth, and wiſdom, which all your adverſaries ſhall not be able to gain-ſay, nor reſist,</hi> Luke 21.15. he commended them not to Pagan Schools, to <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> or <hi>Plato,</hi> or any other Heathen, to enable them to refute Hereſies, but to his own gift, his wiſdom, Armour of proof, his own Sword put into the hands, enabling for his work.</p>
               <p>We read not that the ancient Chriſtians ever taught Philoſophy openly, and in Schools, but that they rather gain-ſayed it, Pagan. <hi>Gaudentius Theol de moribus ſeculi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let any one ſhew me (ſaith this Author) that Philoſophy was taught by Chriſtians, in the time of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> or before.</p>
               <p>Scarce any one can be perſwaded (ſaith this Author) that Chriſtian Emperors would command, that a Heathen Philoſopher, in the Capitol of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould teach the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of Pagan Philoſophers, to Chriſtians; this would have been to introduce, or bring in old Superſtition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtin</hi> paſſed to the Church, becauſe he found no certainty in the School of <hi>Plato;</hi> he turned from <hi>Plato,</hi> and the reſt of the Heathen Philoſophers, and addicted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Scriptures of Truth. <hi>Gaudentius de mor. ſeculi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. Celius Lactantius</hi> ſaid, I verily cannot
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:110312:32"/>call them Philoſophers, that ſtudy for wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, becauſe by that ſtudy they do not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto wiſdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard Fitz-Ralph,</hi> called <hi>Armachanus,</hi> in a Sermon preached before the Popes Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals in the year 1360. ſaid, Laymen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain from ſending their Sons to the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, fearing to have them taken from them; chuſing rather to keep their Sons at home, and breed them to Husbandry, then to loſe them, by ſending them to the Schools.</p>
               <p>In a Synod holden at <hi>Guernſey</hi> 1576. and confirmed by a Synod held there 1597. for the Eſtate of <hi>Guernſey</hi> and <hi>Jerſey,</hi> it was provided in behalf of School-maſters, that they ſhould inſtruct their Scholars in the moſt pure Authors both for learning and language, leſt Children by reading laſcivions and immodeſt writings, ſhould be infected with their venom; as may be ſeen in a Book called, <hi>Heylyn</hi>'s Survey of the State of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Georgius Ederus</hi> in his <hi>Mateologia Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticorum,</hi> greatly inveighs againſt <hi>Wickliff,</hi> and charges him with ſaying, That Studies were vanities brought into the Church, and profits the Church no more, then the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil doth.</p>
               <p>In the days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Lords of her Privy-Councel ſent Letters to her
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:110312:32"/>High Commiſſioners in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, requiring them to write Letters to all the Biſhops of this Realm, and to require them to give commandment, that in all Grammar and Free-Schools within their ſeveral Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, <hi>Chriſtopher Ockland</hi>'s Book intituled <hi>Anglorum praelia,</hi> ſhould be taught, in place of ſome Heathen Poets; ſaying, the Youth of the Realm receives rather infections in manners, then advancement in virtue, from the Heathen Poets taught in Schools: They prayed and required, that this might be done for the encouragement of the ſaid <hi>Ockland,</hi> and others travelling in the like Studies, and for the removing of laſcivious Poets, taught in Schools. The names of the Lords of the Privy-Councel, as alſo of her High Commiſſioners in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, as alſo their Letters, are to be ſeen at the beginning of the Book called <hi>Anglorum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia:</hi> The aforeſaid Commiſſioners directed their Letters to all the Biſhops of the Queens Dominions of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of the aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Men have neglected ſound, ſavoury, and uſeful matter, the very quinteſſence of Learning, and have devoted themſelves to an exceſs of fine ſpeaking. Biſhop <hi>Wilkins</hi> Real Character.</p>
               <p>The grand impoſture of phraſing, hath eaten out all ſolid learning. B. <hi>Wilkins.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:110312:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caeſar Caracalla</hi> ſo doated upon the name of <hi>Alexander,</hi> that he was highly offended that a lewd Murtherer called <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſhould be queſtioned for his miſdemeanour, ſaying, Accuſeſt thou <hi>Alexander?</hi> unleſs thou be ſilent concerning <hi>Alexander,</hi> thou art an undone man. Beware leſt in loving the name of Philoſophy, ye embrace Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy with its errors. <hi>Orat. Doct. Ran.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaid, that Hereſies are propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> by the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> by <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures,</hi> by <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> by <hi>Zeno,</hi> by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> by worldly wiſdom. <hi>Orat. Ranoldi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ludovicus Vives, Picus Mirandula, Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymus Savonarola,</hi> taught, that Chriſtians were not to read <hi>Aristotle</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> except very warily, <hi>Orat. Ranoldi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the Philoſophy of <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> peſtilent errors firſt of all invaded, and have long poſſeſſed, and at this day do waſte the Chriſtian Church. <hi>Orat. Ranoldi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The World is ſo bewitched by the delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Satan, that the errors of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, through vain and rotten diſtinctions, are defended of thoſe called Chriſtians, in their publick Aſſemblies; hereby they have brought it to paſs, that the Faith of Chriſt hath no reſidence in the hearts of many who profeſs him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in his Confeſſions, accounts <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> a Comical Poet, unworthy to be read
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110312:33"/>and blames Grammarians for teaching of it. <hi>Orat. Ranoldi.</hi> This ſs accounted a delicate diſh now in Schools, though profeſſing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
               <p>Philoſophers of old ſtained the <hi>Greek</hi> Church with various errors; in this our day they have polluted all <hi>Italy,</hi> with their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous opinions, and I wiſh it were but <hi>Italy</hi> only. <hi>Orat. Ranoldi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Far be it from us (ſaith <hi>Jerom,</hi> who lived about the year 384.) that omnipotent <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter, Mecastor,</hi> and other Monſters, rather then Gods, ſhould be heard out of the mouth of a Chriſtian. <hi>Orat. Ranoldi.</hi> And ſcarce any other thing rings in Schools now.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council of choſen Cardinals, they called it a grand and a deſtructive abuſe, that Profeſſors of Philoſophy taught wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in publick Schools. <hi>Orat. Ranoldi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Under the name of Nature, (ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> of old) enemies of Grace lie hid; ſo in our days, under the name of Philoſophy, the enemies of Faith lie hid. <hi>Orat. Ranoldi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> reigns, there ungodlineſs hath great dominion. <hi>Orat. Ranoldi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What other thing did <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, when he endeavoured to ſweep Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion from off the face of the Earth, then provide that thoſe opinions ſhould be taught, defended, and declaimed in Schools, which gain-ſayed Chriſtianity. <hi>Orat. Ranoldi.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:110312:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maximinus</hi> a tyrannical Emperor, who reigned about the year 336. was blamed by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> becauſe he gave way, or wiſhed, that thoſe things ſhould be taught and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Schools, which were contrary to ſound godlineſs. <hi>Orat. Ranoldi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How foul a thing is it, that that may be ſpoken againſt you, which <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpoke of the <hi>Arians,</hi> they have deſerted the Apoſtle, and they follow <hi>Ariſtotle. Orat. Ranoldi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No honour nor regard was given to the Art of Poetry before; moreover it was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſo infamous, that if any man was inclinable to the ſtudy thereof, he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Robber. <hi>Polydor lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hadrian Saraviah</hi> informs us, that the Primitive Chriſtians had no Academical Schools, like to theſe now a-days: Yet there was one at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> where they read only Divinity.</p>
               <p>We read not of any Univerſities among the <hi>Waldenſes, Albigenſes,</hi> and <hi>Bothemians,</hi> for moſt of their Miniſters were Tradeſmen.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians in the Primitive times found Sophiſters, and Philoſophers, to be the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal enemies of Chriſtianity; upon this account they condemned all Heathen lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they condemned Comedies and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies, and other Poetical writings, judging they did not conduce to ſolid knowledge. <hi>Herrald. animad. in Arnob.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:110312:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> judged that Schoolmaſters pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Learning, were guilty of great Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, becauſe they only explained Names and Genealogies, and fabulous Acts of Heathen gods, Tertul. <hi>de Idolatr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſee (ſaith <hi>Gracian</hi>) that the Prieſts of the Lord, neglecting the Goſpel and the Prophets, they read Comedies, and Love Verſes out of <hi>Bucolicks;</hi> they peruſe <hi>Virgil:</hi> and what is a ſin of inforced neceſſity in Children, is become their delight: Doth he not ſeem to walk in Vanity, and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, who vexes himſelf day and night in the Study of Logick, and charges his Memory with the diſtinct knowledge of Verſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus Bellonius</hi> ſaith, that there were many Chriſtians in <hi>Creece,</hi> but few Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men among them; becauſe they eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not of it as of neceſſity to Chriſtianity: In their Libraries were ſeveral Manuſcripts of Divinity; but no Hiſtorian, nor Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, nor Poet, for theſe were Anethemized.</p>
               <p>Neither the <hi>Greeks</hi> nor the <hi>Pickards,</hi> nor <hi>Waldenſes</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> did value Learning, Luther <hi>de inſtitutione puerorum, fol.</hi> 444.</p>
               <p>It was an Article exhibited againſt <hi>John Wicklif,</hi> Condemned at <hi>Conſtance,</hi> who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd as a Martyr; that Graduations and Doctorſhips in Univerſities and Colledges, then in uſe, did conduce nothing to the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:110312:35"/>Church of Chriſt, for Acts and Monuments.</p>
               <p>Colledge Doctors have for their Arms, the Book with ſeven Seals; and why? becauſe they are skil'd in the ſeven Liberal Arts, which is abſurd, and fooliſh, if not Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous; as though the ſeven Liberal Arts, as Grammar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> could open the Book with ſeven Seals, 'tis the Lamb only.</p>
               <p>The Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> had an expreſs Canon againſt the reading of Heathen Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, <hi>Conc Carth. Diſt. cap.</hi> 37.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> though a Pope, burnt ſeveral Laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civious Authors, as <hi>Carden</hi> tells us, <hi>de ſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>In like manner <hi>Gregory Nazianzen.</hi> the Father, ſuppreſſed ſeveral Greek Authors, as <hi>Diphiles, Apollodonus, Philemon, Alexis, Sappho,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Machivael</hi> teſtifies, that the firſt promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Chriſtianity, commanded all Poets and Hiſtorians, which treated of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles vain Converſation and Worſhip to be burned, <hi>Mach. Diſp. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>'Tis written by one in the life of <hi>Jerom,</hi> that he was a great Student in Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, Caldean, and Syrian Tongues, and much in love with <hi>Tullies</hi> Eloquence; being in a Fever he was brought in the Spirit to the Judgment Seat of Chriſt; being exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, he ſaid he was a Chriſtian; the Judge replyed, thou ſeemſt to be rather a <hi>Ciceroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:110312:35"/>then a Chriſtian, for where thy Treaſure is, there is thy life alſo: On this occaſion <hi>Jerom</hi> rejected Heathen Books and Fables, unprofitable and vain Studies; writing to Pope <hi>Damaſus,</hi> he reproved Eccleſiaſtical perſons, for neglecting Holy Scriptures, and ſpending their time in Heatheniſh Books and Fables.</p>
               <p>Men of unqueſtionable worth (ſaith <hi>Dell</hi>) ſeeing the evil of ſpoiling Philoſophy, have ſpoken freely againſt Univerſities ſtained thereby: <hi>Wicklif</hi> tells them, <hi>Caſtra Caini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,</hi> that is, <hi>Cains</hi> Caſtles, <hi>Satans</hi> Synagogues; affirming that they were never inſtituted by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Hus,</hi> or <hi>Otho Brunſelſius,</hi> if he ſet out the Contents of the Chapter, calls them <hi>Satrapas Antichriſti,</hi> the Lieutenants of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> in his Book againſt <hi>Ambroſius Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharinus,</hi> ſaith, that Univerſities are an open gate of hell, and that therein the moſt choice Youth of Chriſtian people are proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, and caſt into the open throat of Hell.</p>
               <p>Further he ſaith, that whoſoever firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and confirmed Univerſities, he was a Star fallen from Heaven to Earth, from the Goſpel of Chriſt to humane Learning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Melancthon</hi> termed the Univerſities, houſes of Lies; ſaying further, that Students in Univerſities, are not people of the Goſpel,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110312:36"/>nor yet of the Law, but are the people of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Morals.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Theſe ſpoke againſt Popiſh Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and they are otherwiſe now. 'Tis true (ſaith <hi>Dell</hi>) the outward form of groſs Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery is taken away from them, as from the Nation; yet the Inner part of it remains as before, the ſelf ſame Statutes of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities remain in force, which were firſt given by Popiſh Founders; again, the ſame Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy of Heatheniſm is inſtilled now into Youth, as in the darkeſt dayes of Popery, the ſelf ſame outward and Antichriſtian Forms and Follies ſtill remain as in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt o Popery, even unto their Hoods, Caps, Scarlet Robes, Doctoral Rings, Gloves, their Doctoral Dinner and Muſick.</p>
               <p>To this day preſently after their Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Acts, (ſaid this <hi>Dell</hi>) they have their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicator; a notable Varlet, picked out of the Univerſities, who in the preſence of all the Heads, Students, Scholars, and the great reſort of Miniſters and People at their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement; Abuſes, Derides, and Jeers all ſorts of perſons, of all Ages, Sexes, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions; ſuch works of Levity were never allowable among the Holy men of God. Chriſt ſaid, have Salt in your ſelves, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdom, with which thoſe that are ſeaſoned, cannot but ſavour, and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend ſuch things to be unſavoury.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:110312:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> lived about the year 150. He, (as 'tis related in his Dialogue with <hi>Trypho</hi>) firſt joyned himſelf to that Sect of Philoſophers called Stoicks, after to the Peripatetic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, after to the Pythagorean Sect, after to the Platoniſts; being Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, he wholly left his Philoſophy, and Philoſophical apprehenſions, and betook himſelf to the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperor took care that the Scriptures might be taught to people, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it moſt meet that Chriſtians ſhould be inſtructed in the Faith of Chriſt, and not in Heatheniſh Philoſophy, <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Through this <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> the Sufferings of the Church vaniſhed; then Chriſtians grew more Carnal and ſecure, even in his days, and began to ſeek after ſpoiling of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy; yet in all Ages God had ſome wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Berno,</hi> who lived in the year 1008. Being furniſhed with all ſorts of Learning, ſaid, that he for many years had rejected Poetical Fictions, Heathen Hiſtorians, Worldly Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as dung, and was wholly minded to ſearch out Heavenly things, Berno <hi>in Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtola ad Magnifred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zuinglius</hi> in his Youth was exerciſed in all ſorts of Learning: In the end he intreated the Lord to vouchſafe him his own Light; ſaying, what he had Learned before from
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:110312:37"/>Philoſophers, procur'd him much trouble: and he rejected Phyloſophy, and counted it as dung, Zuingl. <hi>de veritate Verbi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Schools and Univerſities were at firſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, by declining the pure word of the Goſpel, and entertaining Philoſophy and Heathen Authors, <hi>Dell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matthias Pariſienſis</hi> a <hi>Bohemian</hi> by Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, about the year 1580. wrote a Book againſt Antichriſt; wherein he affirms, that Antichriſt had deceived and miſled all Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities and Colledges of the Learned, ſo that now, ſaith he, they teach no ſound thing, neither give they true light unto Chriſtians by their Doctrine, <hi>Illeryc. Flair. Catal. Teſt. Veritat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Antichriſt (ſaith <hi>John Hus</hi>) hath drawn men aſide from the wiſdom of God reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Salvation, and with the Holy Spirit, to the prudence and wiſdom of men, and of the Princes of this World, <hi>de Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christo, cap.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martin Luther</hi> ſaid, whoſoever it was; whether <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hales,</hi> or <hi>Thomas Aquine,</hi> who firſt inſtituted Univerſities; he was a Star fallen from Heaven to Earth, Luther <hi>de Captiv.</hi> Babylon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abbas Joachim Calaber</hi> about the year 1230. in his Commentary on <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſpeaks to this purpoſe; that the firſt Angel men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, in <hi>Revelations</hi> the ninth, opens the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:110312:37"/>bottomleſs pit, and brings forth Philoſophy into the Church; and out of this ſmoak of this Doctrine proceeded Locuſts, and theſe Locuſts, ſaid he, are Schoolmen and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who ſometime uſe Flattery to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, ſometime Rigour to ſubvert the ſimple and unwary.</p>
               <p>The Lord ſtirr'd up <hi>Julian</hi> (ſaith he) to put down Heathen Learning in Chriſtian Schools; that it might appear, that as the true Chriſtian Religion is not helped by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Learning, ſo neither is it hindred by the want of it. <hi>Rainold</hi> in his Orations ſaith the contrary of this <hi>Julian;</hi> but times and ends being conſidered, they are eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled.</p>
               <p>The Queen of the South neglecting the <hi>Magi,</hi> Philoſophers, Heathen Wiſemen, came from the utmoſt parts of the earth to hear Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon;</hi> but Schools and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities leave Chriſt, greater then <hi>Solomon,</hi> in whom are all Treaſures of wiſdom and knowledge, and ſeeks knowledge from the Heathen, as <hi>Ariſtotle, Plato</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates Scholaſticus</hi> ſaith, that for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians thoroughly to imbibe the Learning of the Heathen, it can no way advantage Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, for it is not without danger, for Chriſtians to be inſtructed in Heathen Learning, becauſe it teacheth a plurality of gods, that there are many gods, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:110312:38"/>
               <p>My advice is (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) that Youth ſhun Philoſophy and School Divinity, as the death of the Soul, <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 434.</p>
               <p>It is an Error to ſay, that a Divine is not made without <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> rather a Divine is not made unleſs that be done without <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle, Luth. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>I truly judge that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> man <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lif</hi> was a wiſe man; who firſt of all, as far as I know ſaw that Univerſities were Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans Synagogues, <hi>Melancthon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing Chriſt Inſtituted not thoſe Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, (ſaith <hi>Wicklif,</hi>) or Colledges, it ſeems evident, that they, as Graduations in them, are vain Heatheniſm brought in; in token of this, both Collegiates, and other Graduates ſeek themſelves. This <hi>Wicklif</hi> was Maſter of <hi>Baliol</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lif <hi>in ſpeculo Militantis Eccleſiae, cap.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>We muſt make inquiry of Schoolmaſters and other profeſſors of Learning, teaching Heathen Gods, their Names, Genealogies, and Fables: Yea we need not doubt, but that they are guilty of Idolatry of divers ſorts, <hi>Tertul de Idolatr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Chriſtian Schoolmaſter by his frequent reading of Poets, defilements of Idols; he ſeems to allow of theſe things, <hi>Regaltius in Tertullianum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates</hi> drove out of the City lewd De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and Atchievers of Naughtineſs, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:110312:38"/>by Poets, and he taught men to ſhun <hi>Homer,</hi> and other Poets; and he exhorted them after the ſearch of the living God, whom they were ignorant of, <hi>Justini pro Chriſtianis apologio prima.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Abſtain from all Heathen Books, ſaith <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> ſaying further; what is wanting in the Law of God, that thou ſhould apply thy mind unto Heathen Fables, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>What madneſs poſſeſſes the minds of men, that they ſhould regard <hi>Jupiter;</hi> whom they do not only know to be an ungodly man, Wicked, Profane, Whoriſh, a patricid; but alſo ſing to him on the Stage: The Ancients denyed theſe things, but now through a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of inſtructing Youth, the knowledge of theſe things is ſo incorporated in tender and ſimple minds, as that the ſame can ſcarce by any way or means be rid out of them, <hi>Recognit. Clement. lib.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtin</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hippo,</hi> commanded Poetry to be driven out of the City of God, ſo alſo did <hi>Ethnick Plato,</hi> out of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; <hi>Cicero</hi> forbad the ſame to be entertained, <hi>Cor. Agrip. Devan. Scient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtin</hi> called Heathen Poetry the Wine of Error, drunk of drunken Doctors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jerom</hi> called it the meat of Devils.</p>
               <p>Logick is nothing but the Art of Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Darkneſs, whereby all other Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:110312:39"/>are made more obſure, and more hard to be known, <hi>Cornel. Agrip. de vanitate Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiarum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Almoſt all the rabble of Schollars buſied in the inventions of Philoſophers, or Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, ſeems to do no more, then learn to commit Error, and to make the Truth more obſcure, or to loſe the ſame, <hi>Carnel. Agrip. de vanitate Scientiarum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> enjoyned, that School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters ſhould accuſtom their Schollers, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently to learn ſuch Sentences of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as ſhould be moſt expedient to induce them to all godlineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tindal</hi> a Martyr ſaid, whoſoever ordained Univerſities, be it <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hales, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aquinas,</hi> or any other, he was a Star fallen from Heaven to Earth; for there are brought in (ſaith he) Moral vertues for Faith, Opinions for Truth, and ſaid, they were a confuſed cloud, <hi>Tindal</hi> of the Revelation of Antichriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:110312:39"/>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> A memento to Schoolmaſters and Tutors, to turn from Heathen, to the godly and Chriſtian education of Youth; as alſo of the riſe of Chriſtian Schools, and how the ſame came to be corrupted.</head>
               <p>NOw O Schoolmaſters and inſtructers of Youth, in Schools and Colledges, let me come nearer unto you, 'tis not Schools, but corrupting, ſpoiling and depraving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes therein managed, I ſpeak againſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> could ſay, we cannot any wiſe do the Common-wealth more ſervice, then by teaching and inſtructing Youth, provided (ſaith I) it be in the knowledge of the Lord, of his Creation, of ſavoury and neceſſary things and uſeful accompliſhments.</p>
               <p>Let me tell you, I oppoſe not Teaching or Learning of Languages, as of Latin, Greek, or Hebrew, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Knowing there may be a ſervice therein, for the management of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Tranſactions, and Negotiations, and Correſpondence with other Nations; but it being that all ſavoury and ſound knowledge relates primarily to God, ſecondarily to the knowledge of the Creation, and of the uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:110312:40"/>and neceſſary imployments My Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is, that Children ſhould be inſtructed in the aforeſaid, in the fear of the Lord, it being the door of Heavenly wiſdom.</p>
               <p>How precious were it, if their Souls like <hi>Gideons</hi> Fleece, did drink up betime the pearly dew of Divine Grace, and Heavenly vertue: 'Tis honourable (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) for Youth to be found in the fear of the living God; 'tis the Devil, his Books, and his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which is earthly, ſenſual, and deviliſh, I ſpeak againſt, if in learning of Languages; uſeful, profitable, and neceſſary matter were learned; a double advantage would accrue unto the learner, cannot Languages be learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, except in the Devils Books and Arts?</p>
               <p>I teſtifie that all laſcivious Poems, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Comedies, vain Tragedies, frivolous Fables, inchanting Orations, ſpoiling Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, Pagan Ethicks, Phyſicks, and Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks, now taught in Chriſtian Schools, are the muddy ſtreams of the lying Spirit, and to be denyed by ſerious Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>You may read that the Patriarchs before the Law, taught their Children and Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds, to walk in the ways of the Lord; they taught them not Heatheniſm, nor Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Inventions, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.17, 19.</p>
               <p>Under the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Deſpenſation, the Prophets had Schools, wherein they taught Youth the knowledge of the Lord, the Book
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:110312:40"/>of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets then extant; they taught no Heatheniſh learning, no <hi>Egyptian</hi> Philoſophy, nor the <hi>Smaragdine</hi> Table of <hi>Hermes Triſmegiſtus,</hi> during the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of that Miniſtration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh that there were ſuch an heart in</hi> Iſrael, (ſaid the Lord) <hi>to fear me and to keep all my Commandments always, that it might go well with them, and with their Children for ever,</hi> Deut. 5.29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon,</hi> wiſe in the wiſdom of God, ſaid, <hi>Train up a Child in the way he ſhould go, and when he is old, he will not depart from it,</hi> Prov. 22.6. He ſhould go in the way of holineſs, in which the ranſomed of the Lord walk, with ſongs of deliverance in their mouths: Children are to be trained up in the Lords way; not in Heatheniſm, Serpentine inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Heathen Philoſophy, laſcivious Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, and Tragedies, frivolous Fables; theſe things are in the Devils way: I ſaw it in the glaſs of Immortality, in the lamp of Eternity, in the ſin-diſcovering diſpenſation of the Almighty, that ſuch as teach theſe things, they are Satans Cooks, preparing a deadly diſh; Satans Butlers, making Youth drunk with the Cup of Abomination, and Fornication, a ruſty Channel, through whom a ſtream of folly enters into thoſe committed to their charge, which nothing but a Divine rod can drive out, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.15.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:110312:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> the ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael</hi> enquired, ſaying, <hi>Wherewith ſhall a young man cleanſe his way? in taking heed thereto according to the word,</hi> Pſal. 119.9. He commends young men to the word, the word of Faith, of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, of Reconciliation, of Vivification, that they may be cleanſed and purified there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; he commends them not to Paganiſm, Ethnick Education, ſpoiling Philoſophy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord</hi> (ſaith the holy man of God) <hi>eſtabliſhed a Teſtimony in</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ordained a Law in</hi> Iſrael <hi>which he commanded our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that they ſhould teach their Children, that Children which ſhould be born, ſhould ſtand up and declare it to their Children,</hi> Pſal. 78.5, 6. The Teſtimony and Law of the Lord; was to be propagated and taught to young and old in that Diſpenſation, the wiſdom of God which cauſes the face to ſhine, and fills the inward parts with joyful Melody, not Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine wiſdom, the wiſdom of this World, the Dictates of the Internal Dragon, drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men in perdition.</p>
               <p>Further, the Lord ſaid, <hi>Learn not the way of the Heathen,</hi> Jeremiah 10.2. Now all Heathen Philoſophy, Ethicks, Phyſicks, and Metaphyſicks, Heathen Poets, Comedies, Tragedies, and Fables, are the way of the Heathen, ſo not to be learned; the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Serpent, to be rejected: when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was ſtained with the Inventions of the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:110312:41"/>Heathen, the Lord raiſed complaints againſt them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.</p>
               <p>As the holy men of God in the Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal and Moſaical diſpenſations, through the ſhield of Faith fenc'd out the wiſdom of the Fleſh; So in the Evangelical diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Diſciples and Apoſtles of the Lamb, kept the ſame, and laboured in the vertue and ſtrength of Divine abilities, committed to them, to bring them to Chriſt, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine, Repoſitory, and ſtore-houſe of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdom and knowledge.</p>
               <p>Chriſt Jeſus (ſaith <hi>Hoſpinian de Origine Scholarum</hi>) inſtituted the firſt Academy in the New Teſtament, and called twelve Diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciples, whom he diligently inſtructed in Heavenly Doctrine; he taught them no Heathen Philoſophy, nor Traditions of men.</p>
               <p>After the Reſurrection of Chriſt, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles being well confirmed in his School, and furniſhed with the gifts of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; went out into the World according to Chriſts command, and commended unto others what they had learned of Chriſt, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpinian, Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Go and teach all Nations,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Teaching them to obſerve all things, whatſoever I have commanded you;</hi> what, and only what they received from Chriſt; that, and only that they were to teach others; but no Heathen Philoſophy, nor Traditions of men, dropped out of their
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:110312:42"/>Mouths; but their living concerns was to bring them to learn of Chriſt the wiſdom of God, and to witneſs Salvation, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life through him.</p>
               <p>Further, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to <hi>Timothy, What things thou haſt heard of me in the preſence of many witneſſes, the ſame deliver to faithful men, which ſhall be able to teach others alſo,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.2. Hoſp. But we read not that <hi>Timothy</hi> taught Heathen Philoſophy to any; which plainly demonſtrates, that <hi>Timothy</hi> received no ſuch thing from <hi>Paul,</hi> though he had been brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further, <hi>Paul</hi> who had the mind of Chriſt, writing to Fathers in the behalf of Children, ſaid, <hi>And ye Fathers provoke not your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to wrath, but bring them up in the Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Admonition of the Lord,</hi> Epheſ. 6.4. Not in wanton Poets, Comedies, Tragedies, Fables, the ways of the Heathen.</p>
               <p>The Primitive Biſhop or Elders (ſaith one) had tender regard unto the Children of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and taught them as well as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the knowledge of God in Chriſt, and rejected vain Philoſophy, and Traditions of men, till the Myſtery of iniquity began to inſinuate it ſelf among them, by the means of humain Learning. A School in <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> was inſtituted, not very long after the Apoſtles days; for about the year 182. one <hi>Pantenus</hi> brought up among the Heathen
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:110312:42"/>Stoick Philoſophers, moderated that School, whereby the Doctrine of Chriſt quickly ſpread over the face of the earth, exerciſe in Scriptures flouriſhed among them; at length he travelled as far as <hi>India,</hi> to confirm them in the Faith of Chriſt, <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Hoſpinian,</hi> we read not that he bred them up in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Philoſophy, Poets, Comedies, Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Fables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Afterwards (ſaith this <hi>Hoſpinian</hi>) Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries were built through <hi>Europe,</hi> not through an opinion of any merit, or through any Superſtition; neither that they ſhould be Stews of lewd Fellows, but that they might be as Schools, in which not Children only, but ſuch as were grown up, might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in Piety, Religion, and Heavenly Doctrine, ſo to be capacitated for convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, converting, and building up of others in the ſaving knowledge of the Lord.</p>
               <p>But as <hi>John</hi> foreſaw a Star fall from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto the Earth, to whom the Key of the bottomleſs pit ſhould be given, and that a ſmoak ſhould ariſe out of the pit, Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Doctrines, Humain Traditions, Heathen Learning, ſpoiling Philoſophy, whereby the Sun and the Air, ſhould be darkned, the purity of the Primitive Church, and of Schools, ſhould be ſpoiled, <hi>Revel.</hi> 9. Now as this was fulfilled, the Study of true Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity (ſaith this <hi>Hoſpinian</hi>) began by little
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:110312:43"/>and little to grow cold, to be aboliſhed, and altogether to vaniſh in theſe Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries or Schools; then they invented new opinions concerning Merits, Invocation of Saints, of the Popes Supremacy, of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, of Tranſubſtantiation; this School Divinity taking root and ſpreading, the minds of the ſimple were intangled and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared; the Placeats or Opinions of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Popes, the Writings of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks had ingreſs into Schools, thus Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdom being turned from, the ſmoak of the pit, earthly wiſdom, Heathen Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſteamed into the Churchse and Schools, through which to this day they are clouded, ſtained and corrupted.</p>
               <p>But in reference to the Divinity-School of <hi>Alexandria;</hi> by little and little it ſo dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated and loſt the Heavenly Savour; as that, there hath not been (ſaith the Author of the Book called the <hi>Naked Truth</hi>) a greater plague to Chriſtian Religion then School-Divinity, from which ſprung forth, damnable Hereſies, overſpreading all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.</p>
               <p>Whence did <hi>Paulus Samoſetanus</hi> derive his venomous Hereſies againſt the Son of God? but from <hi>Plotinus,</hi> and his Philoſophick Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations in the School of <hi>Alexandria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did not <hi>Arius,</hi> a Presbyter of the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> imbibe or drink up his blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:110312:43"/>againſt the Divinity of Chriſt, out of the Divinity-School of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> about the year 310. From him ſprung the <hi>Arians,</hi> who over-ran all Chriſtendom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> alſo, and after him <hi>Pelagius,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived their Peſtilent Errours againſt the grace of God, out of the ſame School.</p>
               <p>Thus after the Apoſtles times, the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from above being turned from, the wiſdom, that is from below, being enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Churches and Schools, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy and fall from the Primitive order, life, and ſoundneſs in Doctrine and Converſation, was brought forth.</p>
               <p>If the patern of the Primitive Church, rooted and grounded in Heavenly Wiſdom, Heavenly Philoſophy, (ſaith <hi>Theoph. Gale</hi>) had been obſerved, neither <hi>Origen,</hi> nor <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> nor <hi>Pelagius,</hi> nor <hi>Socinus,</hi> nor the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, nor any of that Company, had been overwhelmed in ſo many monſtrous Errours.</p>
               <p>Many of the Primitive Doctors and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, (ſaith the Author of the Book called the <hi>Naked Truth</hi>) being converted from Heatheniſm, greatly skil'd in Natural Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, Antiquity, Hiſtory, Subtil Logick, or Sophiſtry, were unwilling to abandom their long ſtudied and beloved Sciences ſo called; ſo tranſlated them into Chriſtianity, applying their School Terms, Diſtinctions, Syllogiſms, to Divine matters, ſo defaced Chriſtian knowledge.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:110312:44"/>
               <p>Thus through the ſteaming in of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm, into Church and School, the pure, ſound, ſavoury Education of Youth in the knowledge of the Lord, was loſt, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving, ſpoiling, corrupting education en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in, out of lewd Poems, Comedies, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies, Fables, ſpoiling Philoſophy, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued yet in Chriſtendom. I doubt not (faith our Country man <hi>Dell</hi>) but ſome men ſhew more care and pains, to teach a Colt to Pace and Amble, then they do to inſtruct their Children to walk in the way of Gods Commandments.</p>
               <p>Further, you Maſters in Schools and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, who inſtruct Youth in Prophane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, Arts and Sciences, as the Lamp of Eternity is lighted in you, you will ſee you have been dancing after the Popes Pipe, yea after the Serpents Pipe, the Author of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm.</p>
               <p>You may read, that in the time of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Heptarchie, <hi>Auſtine</hi> the Monk with others, came from <hi>Rome</hi> into this Nation; and the Faith, and School-Education of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal <hi>Rome,</hi> was received by the <hi>Saxons,</hi> ſo that many Authors came into our Schools, by and through them, which are yet conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sigebert</hi> King of the <hi>Eaſt-Angles,</hi> having learned in <hi>France</hi> the manner of their Schools, with aſſiſtance of ſome Teachers out of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:110312:44"/>
                  <hi>Kent,</hi> inſtituted after the ſame Diſcipline, the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> then firſt found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, about the year 630. This <hi>Sigebert</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward changed his Royal Robe for a Hood.</p>
               <p>About the year 668. by means of <hi>Theodore</hi> a learned Greekiſh Monk of <hi>Tarſus,</hi> whom Pope <hi>Vitalian</hi> had ordained Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> the Greek and Latin Tongue with other liberal Arts, as Arithmatick, Muſick, Aſtronomy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> began firſt to flouriſh among the <hi>Saxons,</hi> ſaith <hi>Milton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the Council of four Monks, Schollars of <hi>Bede,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dell</hi>) to wit, <hi>Rabanus, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binus, Claudius,</hi> and <hi>John Scotus,</hi> the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity which had been tranſlated from <hi>Athens</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> was tranſlated by <hi>Charles</hi> the great from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> about the year 791.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Cambridge</hi> was made an Univerſity by King <hi>Sigebert</hi> of the Romiſh Faith, and the Lectures there were begun by four Monks; Fryer <hi>Ode</hi> read Grammar, <hi>Tericus</hi> read <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Logicks, Fryer <hi>William</hi> read <hi>Tullies</hi> Rhetorick, <hi>Dilſebert</hi> read Divinity to them on <hi>Sundays</hi> and Saints days ſo called.</p>
               <p>About the year 895. King <hi>Alfred,</hi> through the perſwaſion of Monk <hi>Neotus,</hi> made <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> a publick Univerſity, and appointed Maintenance for the Profeſſors of Learning there, as ſaith <hi>Georg. Lilius</hi> in <hi>Chron. Britt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After both theſe places of Literature were
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:110312:45"/>made or confirmed Univerſities in <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt his time; by the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Robert Remington</hi> affirms.</p>
               <p>The very names of the Colledges diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Founders, as <hi>Chriſts Colledge, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Colledge, Immanual Colledge, Trinity Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Corpus Chriſti,</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſts body Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> and one in <hi>Oxford</hi> for the help of all dead Souls, and for their reſcue out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, called <hi>All Souls Colledge.</hi> Now how theſe Collegians ſhew forth the Spirit of Chriſt by their Fruits, and how their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment is to ſuch as in faith and patience wait for the Kingdom of Chriſt, and the righteouſneſs thereof; or whether they be as the Lilie among the Thorns, or as the Thorns, Heave another pen to diſcover.</p>
               <p>Univerſities to gain the greater profit to themſelves, give divers Degrees and Titles, as Bachelors of Arts, Maſters of Arts, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelors of Divinity, Doctors of Divinty; whereby (ſaith <hi>Dell</hi>) they gain Honour, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, and Reputation, among all that are under the deluſion of Antichriſt; true it is, <hi>a principio non it a fuit:</hi> 'Twas not ſo from the beginning, till the Star fell from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Earth, and the ſmoak aroſe out of the Pit, darkening Sun and Air, theſe things were not, in ſeven years in Univerſities; they are Maſters of Art, as an Apprentice is Maſter of his Trade, having ſerved ſeven
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:110312:45"/>years: Papiſts made their Miniſters in theſe places, as the Proteſtants do now; the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy there taught now, is the ſame, that the Heathen <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors ſet up; they cauſed to be taught, Grammar and Logick, and moſt of the ſeven Arts, as now.</p>
               <p>The Vicechancellor admitting a Bachelor of Divinity to his Degree, uſes theſe words, <hi>We admit thee to preach all the Apoſtolical Epiſtles, in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Spirit.</hi> But,</p>
               <p>Admitting a Doctor of Divinity to his Degree, he ſaith, <hi>We admit thee to preach all the Sacred Scriptures, both of the Old, and of the New Teſtament, in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit,</hi> cap. 20. <hi>de Ceremoniis in gradibus conferendis,</hi> Zuinglius.</p>
               <p>In the Primitive times, ſuch as were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of the Lord, they waited for Heavenly Abilities, to be capacitated to beget others into the life of Righteouſneſs, and to build them up in the moſt holy Faith; they did not ambitiouſſy affect Titles out of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving life; the Phariſees were guilty of this, as formal Chriſtians were: After the ingreſs, and inrode of Apoſtaſy, <hi>Zuinglius</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. ſaid, Thou heare hereſt, that the Titles of Maſters and Doctors, are not of God, becauſe Chriſt forbids this thing; and thoſe Titles that are not of God, nor of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:110312:46"/>Chriſt, they are of Antichriſt, ſo to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed by ſuch as are branches of the true Vine. Further, <hi>Wilſon</hi> in his <hi>Compleat Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Dictionary,</hi> ſaid, that ambitious ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after Titles ought to be eſchewed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> In the Apoſtles days there were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Titles, as Evangeliſts, Apoſtles, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Paſtors, Doctors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> True it is, but theſe and the reſt made uſe of, or mentioned in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were ſignificant names, names of Office, befitting and expreſſing the work they were called unto, and concerned in, as I might particularize; as for Doctor, it might more properly be tranſlated Teacher; ſo a name of Office, <hi>Wicklif</hi> touching this thing, ſaid, a name of Office differs much from the name of a School Degree, brought in by the Heathen, <hi>Wicklif, in ſermone domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni in Monte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>While the Primitive purity, Life, Power, Faith and Order was kept; he that mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, he was to do it, out of the ability which God gave, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. The power of the Miniſtry was derived from the pure Spring of Divine ability, but this ability be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loſt, Schools were erected, Heathen Learning was entertained; where men are qualified now for the Miniſtry, this muddy lake, open in <hi>Rome</hi>-Heathen, ſteamed into Apoſtatiſed <hi>Rome</hi>-Chriſtian, drunk up in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:110312:46"/>Proteſtant Countreys and Kingdoms now.</p>
               <p>To draw to a Concluſion, you Teachers of Schools and Colledges, it being that the ſpecious Fabrick of the World being finiſhed, <hi>God looked upon every thing that he had made, and behold it was very good,</hi> Gen. 1.31. were it not more God-like, more Chriſtian-like, to inſtruct Youth in the knowledge of God, whom to know is life Eternal, and in the knowledge of his works, being very good, and uſeful and neceſſary things, then in the knowledge of Heathen Arts and Sciences, brought in by the Serpent, which in every Age and Generation, the holy men of God; yea and ſuch as have lived in the midnight of Apoſtaſie, with ſome glimpſes of Divine light in their <hi>Goſhen,</hi> bare Teſtimony againſt, as the fore-mentioned Teſtimonies, with others that might have been ſubjoyned ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently evidence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> in the wiſdom of God, ſaid, <hi>The works of the Lord are wonderful, ſought out of all them that have pleaſure therein,</hi> Pſal. 111.2. Such as have pleaſure in the Lord, cannot but have pleaſure in his works: Now you that make Heatheniſm your concern, you neither have pleaſure in the Lord, nor in his works, which are very good.</p>
               <p>Further, <hi>David</hi> in the conſideration of the Lord; broke out, ſaying, <hi>Lord, how manifold are thy works, in wiſdom thou haſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:110312:47"/>made them all, the earth is full of thy riches, ſo is the great and wide Sea alſo, wherein are things creeping innumerable, both ſmall and great beaſts,</hi> Pſal. 104.24, 25. If man ſhould live the days of <hi>Mathuſelah,</hi> who lived 969. years, yet is the Lord the Book of life, and the Book of Creation, ſufficient for his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; I tell you in downright Tearms, the Lord made man to eye him and his Creation, but the Serpent diſlocating man, brought him to eye him, and his products, and all Heathen Authors, Poems, Comedies, Tragedies, Fables, ſpoiling Philoſophy, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Ethicks, Phyſicks, and Metaphyſicks, are the products of the Serpent, ſo ſee what you do, and where you are.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rainold</hi> in his <hi>Orations,</hi> ſaid, he is to be accounted a wiſe man, who knows things that are profitable; not he that knows many things.</p>
               <p>Now if Languages muſt be Learned, were it not more Chriſtian like, that out of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Books for that purpoſe provided, Children and Youth read the Natures of Trees, Birds, Beaſts, Fiſh, Serpents, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, Earths, Metals, Salts, Stones, Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Precious, as alſo rules for Garden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Agriculture, Grazing of Cattel, Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Navigation, Arithmatick, Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, Chronology, ſound Hiſtory, Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, knowledge in Law, Improvement of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:110312:47"/>Lands, Chirurgery, Traffick Government, ordering of Bees, Propagation of Plants, by Roots, Seeds, Slips, Layers, Suckers, by Graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Inoculating, Imping, and of Geometry, which one <hi>Proclus</hi> aſcribes to to the <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who (the River <hi>Nilus</hi> now and then over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing, confounding and diſordering their Land-marks) found out the uſe and benefit of Geometry; by means of which, every one came to be ſettled in their former and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per right: I ſay, were it not more Chriſtian like, that Children and Youth were inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the knowledge of the Lord, of his Creation, and of neceſſary and uſeful things, whereby they might be qualified for the help, benefit, and advantage of others, in their reſpective Generations; then to be trained up in laſcivious Poems, wanton Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, fooliſh Tragedies, frivolous Fables, Heathen Orations, Pagan Philoſophy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Language of the old Serpent, and of the ſmoak which darkened Sun and Air, after the Primitive times: Certainly (ſaith <hi>Baptiſta Van Helmont</hi> in his Phyſick refined) I could wiſh that the ſpring of Young-men, might not hereafter be ſeaſoned, with ſuch trifles and lying Sophiſtry; they would learn in the ſeven years, Arithmatick, Matha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, Geography, With the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Seas, Rivers, Springs, Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; Provinces, Minerals, the property
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:110312:48"/>and cuſtom of Nations, Plants, living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So by way of recapitulation let me tell you, the knowledge of the Lord, of his Creation, and of uſeful and neceſſary things, I own and deſire propagation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſeeing in meaſure mans ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, before <hi>Abbadon, Apollyon,</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer prevailed, but the knowledge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced by the old Serpent, his Wiſdom, his Poems, his Comedies, vain Tragedies, ſpoiling Philoſophy, Heathen Ethicks, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicks, Metaphyficks, as depriving and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting Youth, I utterly deny: Take the Teſtimony of the Reformer <hi>Martin Luther;</hi> who ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is a ſerious thing, a weighty thing, that Youth be inſtructed in a Godly, and in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian manner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Didſt not thou teach all uſual School Authors, how comeſt thou thus to inveigh againſt them.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, true it is, I taught theſe things, being deeply plunged in the waters of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> waters of bitterneſs; but I found no peace therein, but always entering into the Chamber of ſeriouſneſs, and commencing with the Lord in his Deſpenſation of Grace to me committed; I found the Mouth of Heaven open againſt them, I ſaw them as the full and lothſome matter of an Ulcer,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:110312:48"/>as the Waters of <hi>Babylon,</hi> tranſporting into the region of the ſhadow of death; Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally a dead Sea, in which no man can live unto God; and though I uſed them, after I knew them to be evil, I had no peace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but waited for a deliverance, deſiring of the Lord I might not dye therein, in that heatheniſh muddy concern; but he deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me from the bewitchings of that <hi>Dalilah:</hi> In ſecret retirements ſpiritual reſignation, the abomination and inchantments of the aforeſaid, is more and more diſcovered; I have put off that Coat, and have entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a reſolution, never more to put it on, I have waſhed my Feet, how ſhall I be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed therewith? You that are bound with the delights, bewitchings, or profits of Heatheniſm, of the ſeven liberal Arts, or of any inventions of the Serpent, as <hi>Samſon</hi> was bound with ſeven green Wyths, which he broke as a threed of Tow, when it touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Fire. I tell you the Truth, as it is in Jeſus, as the light which ſhines in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ariſes out of darkneſs, and clears your underſtandings, and gives you the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the excellency of Heavenly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and of the danger of the wiſdom from below, in the luſtre of this, and in Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrength received in it; you will break aſunder the ſeven green Wyths of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching delights of Heatheniſm, of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:110312:49"/>learning, and bear Teſtimony for an education of Youth in the knowledge of the Lord, and of the Creation, and of neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things, expedient for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Yougth for lawful and honeſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in their reſpective Generation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as the Lord opens a door, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement is given, I am ready to be ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; being raiſed to that hope, that <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> muſt fall; as in the particular, ſo muſt he in the General, and her Merchants ceaſe Trading in her proud waves, and that the knowledge which is Heaven-bred, muſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Earth, as Water covers the Sea, and that the wiſdom which is from below, muſt be ſcoured away, as clouds before the wind; ſo be wiſe, and not pillars to ſupport that putrified ſtructure which the Lord is riſen to overturn; 'tis not learning, but unlawful learning; not Schools, but abuſes and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions thereinto crept, that this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is againſt, as the Intelligent Reader may underſtand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:110312:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI. Laſtly,</hi> A few <hi>Queries</hi> ſoberly propoſed to the Conſideration of ſuch as Teach Heathen Authors in Chriſtian Schools.</head>
               <p n="1">IF <hi>Adam</hi> and his poſterity, had kept the ſtate of Innocency, whether ever had we had wanton Poets, and Poems, laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civious Comedies, feigned Tragedies, fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous Fables, ſpoiling Philoſophy; yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether it ought to be the concern of Schoolmaſters as of Miniſters, to eradicate, or propagate, what was introduced, by the Author of the fall?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether to have Teachers in every Pariſh, <hi>vi &amp; armis,</hi> as by force of arms, to drive Heatheniſm into Youth, be the way to eradicate the ſame; yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether man was not created to eye his Creator and the Creation: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether the Serpent Prevalent over man, laid not the foundation of another kingdom: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether wanton Poems, laſcivious Comedies, and Tragedies, frivolous Fables, ſpoiling Philoſophy, taught in Schools, be
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:110312:50"/>not the Language of that Kingdom: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Whether it be not a ſhame to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Schools and Colledges, that Languages cannot, or are not taught, without being beholden to the Heathen: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="8">8. Whether wanton Poems, Comedies, Tragedies, Fables, ſpoiling Philoſophy, were taught to Youth in the Primitive Church before the fall of the Star from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="9">9. Whether wanton Poems, laſcivious Comedies, Tragedies, Fables, ſpoiling Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, be not of the ſmoak that aroſe out of the bottomleſs pit, which darkened the Sun and Air: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="10">10. Whether wanton Poems, Comedies, Tragedies, Fables, ſpoiling Phyloſophy, be not of the foam of that Sea, which the beaſt aroſe out of: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="11">11. Whether the Lord, and his works, which are wonderful, be not ſufficient to take up the ſhort Age of man: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="12">12. Whether wanton Poems, Comedies, Tragedies, Fables, ſpoiling Philoſophy, be not of that knowledge, which puffs up, brought into the World, through the breath of Satans Bellows: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="13">13. Whether wanton Poems, Comedies, Tragedies, Fables, ſpoiling Phyloſophy, were ever kindled in Chriſtian Churches, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:110312:50"/>the old Serpent kindled them, by the breath of his Bellows: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="14">14. Whether laſcivious Poems, Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Tragedies, Fables, ſpoiling Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, be not of that wiſdom, which is earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſenſual and devilliſh: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="15">15. Seeing all the Treaſures of wiſdom and knowledge are in Chriſt; are they not deluded who ſeek the ſame at <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s mouth, or any other Heathen?</p>
               <p n="16">16. Whether wanton Poems, Heathen Comedies, Tragedies, Fables, ſpoiling Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and Idolatrous Traditions; be not dregs of the Cup of Abomination and Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, wherewith Kindreds, Tongues and People, were, and are made drunk: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="17">17. Whether ſuch as Teach theſe things in Schools and Colledges, be not the old Serpents Cooks, preparing a deadly diſh: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="18">18. Whether ſuch as Teach theſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then things, be not eating the forbidden Fruit: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="19">19. Whether it be not Idolatry to Teach, that <hi>Mars</hi> is the god of War, <hi>Bacchus</hi> the god of Wine, <hi>Apollo</hi> the god of wiſdom: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="20">20. Whether Teachers of a plurality of Gods, be not tranſgreſſors of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Goſpel: yea or nay?</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:110312:51"/>
               <p n="21">21. Whether God-fathers and God-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo called, that vow that ſuch and ſuch Children, ſhall forſake the Devil and all his works, pomps and vanities, yet concern themſelves for their Education in laſcivious Poems, Comedies, Tragedies, Fables, ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Philoſophy, be Vow keepers or Vow breakers?</p>
               <p n="22">22. Whether ſuch as are concerned in Teaching wanton Heathen Authors, are not concern'd to keep that alive, which Chriſt comes to deſtroy: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="23">23. Whether ſuch as Teach Heatheniſm in Schools or Colledges, do not labour to keep the Sun and Air darkened by the ſmoak of the pit: yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="24">24. What is the great Star called Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, which fell upon the Rivers and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Waters; and what are the Waters made bitter whereof many dyed, mentioned <hi>Revel.</hi> the 8th.</p>
               <p>In Learning of Languages; wholeſome, ſound, ſavoury, uſeful and neceſſary matter, being Learned, a double advantage (as was ſaid before) accrues to the Learner.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Pura decent puerum; faedis eatemperat aetas</l>
                     <l>A vitiis puerum nil niſi pura decent,</l>
                     <l>Virtutum dulces pueris infunde liquores</l>
                     <l>Et mores aetas promet adulta bonos.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <closer>
                  <signed>T. L.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:110312:51"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
